<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Caves of Qud - Generated Localizable XML 2.0.212.20

<help>

  <topic name="Key" DisplayName="DisplayText">

-->
<help Lang="example" Encoding="utf-8">
  <topic name="Quickstart" DisplayName="▶Quickstart">▶
These are nine things you should do when you start your game.
After that, use the rest of this Help as a reference manual.

{{W|1. Walk around}}

{{?KB|Move by pressing directional keys (~CmdMoveN, ~CmdMoveE, etc) or by clicking on the map.}}{{?Gamepad|Indicate direction with ~UI:Navigate and press ~Take A Step to move or hold ~Take A Step to move continuously.}}{{?Gamepad|
You can also auto-explore the map with ~CmdAutoExplore.}}

{{W|2. Interact with things}}

Walk next to an NPC or other object and press ~CmdUse.

{{W|3. Look at things}}

{{?KB|Press }}~CmdLook to enter Look mode and then move the cursor around the map.{{?KB|
Or {{hotkey|right-click}} to quick look.}}

{{W|4. Use your abilities}}

{{?KB|Click on a button on the ability bar at the bottom of your screen
or press its hotkey.}}{{?Gamepad|Navigate the hotbar at the bottom of your screen with ~UI:Navigate/left and ~UI:Navigate/right
and then press ~Use Ability to use an ability.}}

{{W|5. View your character sheet}}

{{?KB|Press ~CmdCharacter to view your core character info.
Press ~CmdEquipment to view your equipment.
Press ~CmdInventory to view your inventory.
Press ~CmdJournal to view your journal.
Press ~CmdQuests to view your quests.
Press ~CmdSkillsPowers to view your skills.
Press ~CmdFactions to view your faction relationships.

You can scroll through these pages with ~Page Left and ~Page Right.}}{{?Gamepad|Press ~CmdCharacter to view your core character info.
Navigate to other pages in your character sheet with ~Page Left and ~Page Right.}}

{{W|6. Bring up a list of points of interest}}

Press ~CmdMoveToPointOfInterest.

{{W|7. Bring up additional information about objects on the map}}

Press ~Highlight for an overlay with extra info like creature hostility 
(red = hostile, yellow = neutral, green = friendly) and a clear view of 
interesting items.

{{W|8. Walk to another map}}

Simply walk offscreen, or go to the world map with ~CmdMoveU.

{{W|9. Attack an enemy}}

To perform a basic attack, just walk into a hostile creature.
Or you can use an attack ability.
</topic>
  <topic name="Attributes" DisplayName="▶Attributes">▶
[[{{C|Strength}}]]
Your strength score determines how much melee damage you do (by improving 
your armor penetration), your ability to resist forced movement, and your
carry capacity.

[[{{C|Agility}}]]
Your agility score determines your accuracy with both melee and ranged
weapons and your ability to dodge attacks.

[[{{C|Toughness}}]]
Your toughness score determines your number of hit points, your hit point
regeneration rate, and your ability to resist poison and disease.

[[{{C|Intelligence}}]]
Your intelligence score determines your number of skill points and your
ability to examine artifacts.

[[{{C|Willpower}}]]
Your willpower score modifies the cooldowns of your activated abilities,
determines your ability to resist mental attacks, and modifies your hit
point regeneration rate.

[[{{C|Ego}}]]
Your ego score determines the potency of your mental mutations, your
ability to haggle with merchants, and your ability to dominate the wills
of other living creatures.

[[{{C|Armor Value and Dodge Value (AV / DV)}}]]
Your armor value (AV) is a measurement of how well protected you are
against physical attacks that hit you. The higher your score, the less
likely an opponent's attack will do severe damage to you. Most characters
start with a base AV score of 0.

Your dodge value (DV) is a measurement of how likely you are to be hit by
physical attacks. The higher your score, the less likely an opponent's
attack will hit you. Your DV is modified by your Agility modifier. Most
characters start with a base DV of 6.

[[{{C|Mental Armor (MA)}}]]
Your mental armor (MA) is a measurement of how well protected you are
against mental attacks, much as your armor value is a measurement of how
well protected you are from physical attacks. The higher your score, the
less likely an opponent's mental attack will have a severe effect on you.
Your MA is modified by your Willpower modifier. Most characters start
with a base MA of 4.

[[{{C|Quickness (QN)}}]]
Your quickness score is a measurement of how quickly you perform each and
every action you take. Your base quickness score is 100. Note that there
are very few ways to augment this score.

[[{{C|Movement Speed (MS)}}]]
Your movement speed is a measurement of how quickly you walk or fly.
Your base movement speed is 100.

[[{{C|Temperature (T)}}]]
Your temperature is a measurement of how hot or cold you are. If you are
Cold, your quickness score is reduced by half. If you are Frozen, you are
unable to take physical actions. If you are Flaming, you take heat damage
every turn until you reduce your temperature.

[[{{C|Acid Resist}}]]
Your acid resist is a measurement of how much acid damage you ablate. Your
base acid resist score is 0. At 100, you are immune to acid damage.

[[{{C|Cold Resist}}]]
Your cold resist is a measurement of how much cold damage you ablate and how
insulated you are from effects that reduce your temperature. Your base cold
resist score is 0. At 100, you are immune to cold damage and your
temperature cannot be reduced.

[[{{C|Electrical Resist}}]]
Your electrical resist is a measurement of how much electrical damage you
ablate and how resistive you are to electric current. Your base electrical
resist score is 0. At 100, you are immune to electrical damage and you do
not conduct electricity.

[[{{C|Heat Resist}}]]
Your heat resist is a measurement of how much heat damage you ablate and how
insulated you are from effects that increase your temperature. Your base
heat resist score is 0. At 100, you are immune to heat damage and your
temperature cannot be increased.

</topic>
  <topic name="Skills" DisplayName="▶Skills">▶
Your skills represent the abilities you have learned in your
life. Each skill tree has several skills associated with it. You begin with
several skills determined by your caste or calling. You may purchase other
skills by spending skill points which you earn when you gain a level (the
higher your intelligence score, the more skill points you earn).

To purchase a new skill, you must first purchase the entry skill in its
skill tree. You must meet any attribute or power requirements of the skill
you are trying to purchase. It is possible to begin with certain skills 
without having its entry skill if your caste or calling has granted it to
you.

Skills often grant you activated abilities. Once you purchase a skill, you
may access your new activated ability from the Manage Abilities menu ('~CmdAbilities').
</topic>
  <topic name="Mutations and Defects" DisplayName="▶Mutations and Defects">▶
Mutations are special biological powers gifted to the denizens of Qud --
true kin from the outer arcologies do not possess mutations. There are two
types of mutations: physical and mental. Each mutation has a mutation score
associated with it. The scores of your physical mutations and the cooldowns
of activated abilities granted by your physical mutations are static. On
the other hand, the scores of your mental mutations are modified by your
Ego modifier and the cooldowns of abilities granted by your mental
mutations are modulated by 5% for each point of Willpower you possess above
or below 16.

Most characters begin with mutation scores of 1. You earn a mutation point
when you gain a new level which you may spend to augment the score of one
of your mutations by 1. The mutation score of none of your mutations may
exceed 1 plus your character level divided by 2. Additionally, mutations
may only be augmented by mutation points up to a maximum score of 10,
though your mental mutations may exceed this score if your Ego further
augments them beyond 10.

Alternatively, you may spend 4 mutation points to choose a new mutation
from three randomly selected mutations. The mutation you choose begins
with a score of 1. If you are a chimera, you are offered a choice of
physical mutations, if you are an esper, you are offered mental mutations,
otherwise you are offered three completely random mutations. Mutations
often grant you activated abilities. Once you gain a mutation, you may
access your new activated ability from the Manage Abilities menu ('~CmdAbilities').

Defects are mutations with primarily negative effects. Certain mutants
begin with a single defect. There is no score associated with defects.
</topic>
  <topic name="Artifacts" DisplayName="▶Artifacts">▶
Artifacts are items so technologically complex that few of Qud's denizens
understand them. An unidentified artifact will appear to you as a
"Weird Artifact". You may examine an artifact to try to identify it. If you
are successful, you will narrow down the possibilities of that artifact's
function (what was once a "club", for example, you may now identify as a
"rifle"). Eventually you may completely identify the artifact. Each time
you attempt to identify something and fail, however, there is a small
chance you will break it. Your chance of successfully identifying an
artifact is based on your intelligence score.
</topic>
  <topic name="Tonics" DisplayName="▶Tonics">▶
Tonics are chemical concoctions that enhance your mental and physical stats
in a variety of ways. They are artifacts, and so you must successfully
identify them to understand what they do. Ingesting one tonic while under
the effects of another is dangerous; for each new tonic you ingest, there is
a greater and greater chance that the tonics will react adversely to each
other. The higher your Toughness score is, the greater the chance that you
will be able to ingest multiple tonics without incurring undesired effects.

Tonics produce more potent effects in true kin than they do in mutated
humans. Also, as the body chemistry of mutants is inherently unstable,
there is a 5% chance that a tonic ingested by a mutant will instead produce
an undesired effect.

Tonics may be concocted with the Tinker skill. In addition to bits,
concocting a tonic often requires a natural ingredient.
</topic>
  <topic name="Weapons and Armor" DisplayName="▶Weapons and Armor">▶
[[{{C|Weapons}}]]
Every weapon has a penetration value and a damage value
(for example, {{C|→}}4, {{R|♥}}1d4). The penetration value of melee weapons is related
to your strength score, though the value is capped based on the material of
the weapon ('l'ook at a weapon to view its penetration cap). Missile weapons
have static penetration values that do not change based on your strength score.
Weapons may modify other statistics; 'l'ook at a weapon to fully determine
what it does.

[[{{C|Armor}}]]
Most pieces of armor have an armor value and a dodge value
(for example, {{b|♦}}4 {{K|○}}4) that augment your own {{b|♦}}AV and {{K|○}}DV (see {{g|Attributes}}).
Pieces of armor may modify other statistics; 'l'ook at a piece of armor to
fully determine what it does.
</topic>
  <topic name="Combat" DisplayName="▶Combat">▶
[[{{C|Melee Combat}}]]
Melee combat is combat between two adjacent opponents with standard melee
weapons such as swords, daggers, axes, and clubs. To attack a hostile
adjacent opponent, simply move in the direction of the opponent. To attack
something else, such as a non-hostile opponent or a wall, use '~CmdAttackDirection'
and select the direction in which you wish to attack.

When you make a melee attack against a target, the following sequence of
events occurs:

[[{{c|1. Determine whether or not you hit the target.}}]]
Your to-hit roll is 1d20 plus your agility modifier plus any bonuses you
receive from your weapon or skill powers. If this roll exceeds your
opponent's dodge value (DV), then you hit. An empty circle icon over your
target indicates that your attack missed.

[[{{c|2. Determine whether a shield block takes place.}}]]
If the target has a shield equipped, they have a base 25% chance to block
with it, increasing with skill. A successful block adds the shield's armor
value (AV) to the target's AV for this attack.

[[{{c|3. Determine how severely your attack penetrates your target's armor.}}]]
Each weapon has a penetration value ({{C|→}}4, for example). This value
represents the armor value (AV) that your weapon will usually penetrate
with ease. If your weapon's penetration value far exceeds your target's AV,
your weapon will likely penetrate several times. Each time your weapon
penetrates your target's armor, your target is dealt damage equal to your
weapon's damage value ({{R|♥}}1d4, for example). A filled circle icon over your
target indicates that your attack hit but failed to penetrate your target's
armor. A heart icon indicates that your attack hit and penetrated your
target's armor.

[[{{c|4. Determine if multiple attacks are made.}}]]
There is a 15% chance that you make an additional attack with your
secondary hand. Characters with multiple limbs may make additional attacks
beyond this.

[[{{C|Missile Combat}}]]
Missile combat is combat between two opponents with missile weapons such
as bows, pistols, and rifles. To make a missile attack, press '~CmdFire' to aim
your weapon, then '~CmdFire' again to fire.

When you make a missile attack, the following sequence of events occurs:

[[{{c|1. Determine the trajectory of your missile.}}]]
How far a missile is likely to veer from its projected path is determined
by your agility score and the weapon's accuracy.

[[{{c|2. Hit the first medium-sized or larger object along the missile's}}
{{c|trajectory.}}]]

[[{{c|3. Determine how severely the missile penetrates your target's armor.}}]]
This is resolved in the same way as a melee attack.

[[{{c|4. Determine if multiple attacks are made.}}]]
Certain powers allow you to fire multiple missiles with certain missile
weapons.

If you are engaged in melee combat with more than one hostile opponent,
there is a 50% chance that each missile attack you make goes wild (veers
45 degrees to the left or right).
</topic>
  <topic name="Saving Throws" DisplayName="▶Saving Throws">▶
Certain effects or abilities require creatures to make saving throws or face 
consequences. Saving throws each have an attribute and difficulty associated 
with them. To pass a saving throw, a base 1d20 is rolled and then your 
relevant attribute modifier is added. If that number meets or exceeds the 
difficulty, you pass. Otherwise you fail. Some saving throws against 
creature abilities add the creature's attribute modifier to the difficulty 
as well.
</topic>
  <topic name="Action Costs" DisplayName="▶Action Costs">▶
The amount of time it takes to do something is assessed in terms of an
action cost. Most tasks have an action cost of 1000. Your Quickness
increases the rate at which you recover this cost, enabling you to act
more often than slower creatures.

Some skills, mutations, and equipment enable you to take specific actions
at reduced or zero action cost.
</topic>
  <topic name="Credits" DisplayName="▶Credits">▶

                                 [[{{C|Created by}}
                      Brian Bucklew and Jason Grinblat
                      

              QA &amp;&amp; Additional Design - Nick Decapua
              Additional Programming - Corey Frang
                               Music - Craig Hamilton            
                                  QA - Autumn McDonell
              Additional Programming - Bastia Rosen
         Additional Writing &amp;&amp; Design - Caelyn Sandel
                    Additional Music - Brandon Tanner        
                            Tile Art - Samuel Wilson
                Additional UI Design - Polat Yarisci
                        Sound Design - A Shell in the Pit
            QA, Additional Design, &amp;&amp;
              Additional Programming - Thaumatic Systems        
              Additional Programming - Brian Reynolds
                       Legal Counsel - Thomas C. Allison, P.A.
                      
                      Background Art - Cyril van der Haegen
                            Logo Art - Laura &amp;&amp; Jeff Bucholtz
                Community Management - Ivy Melinda &amp;&amp; the mayor team


                                {{C|Published by}}
                                Kitfox Games

                                Tina Liu
                                Xin Ran Liu
                                Alexandra Orlando
                                Tanya X. Short
                                

                                {{C|Special thanks}}
                                Ashenai
                                Riley Vincent
                                Gibbed
                                Floorislava
                                Dr Amazing
                                Devonaut
                                Vaos
                                Tyskil
                                Lakren
                                Stelas
                                Social Animal
                                Contra Duck
                                Saberwulf
                                Megaflare
                                Doctorfrog
                                Palecur
                                NovaPolice
                                Mirdath
                                The Glow
                                Dyzzy
                                Schister
                                Lazybuttons
                                Colonp
                                Niff
                                Matterhorn
                                Clamiam
                                Donraj
                                Randy Marsh
                                Rabbi
                                Getter77
                                Capuchin
                                Wafflecopter
                                Nomikos
                                Magitek
                                Andrew Smash
                                Vastin
                                Frumple
                                Sappho
                                Soulwynd
                                Cpbpunch
                                Tarran
                                Brian Turcotte
                                Oryx
                                Jim Shepard, Dungeonmans
                                MightyMerch
                                Eva Problems, Carbide Chef
                                a nonsense bird
                                Tarn &amp;&amp; Zach Adams
                                

                                {{C|Patrons}}
                                Reed (mutated human) and Tiffany (rabbit)
                                epsalon
                                Tim Linscott
                                Cody, The Rat
                                iconmaster
                                Coal
                                Reuben Eadon
                                Goldkin
                                mdct
                                Rusted Jake Matz
                                Benjamin T. Steed
                                Xerkie!
                                Dij
                                LongueVanne
                                50RCERESS
                                Chef Agate Severance Star
                                awful_falafel
                                Jonny Robertson
                                Ian Wall
                                Orion Perruc-Reyes
                                Ryan Orlando (Fat Thunder)
                                FS Colley
                                Asunaro
                                Trevor Clack
                                Gillian Eggleston
                                Nerem
                                Somsnosa
                                Ivy Sly
                                livelongcoffee
                                SMB64 (Koshi)
                                NO Press
                                EveryZig314
                                Floopygapples
                                Eric Hulen
                                Caine DeWitt
                                Eric Anthony Rodriguez
                                Nathaniel Krell
                                Boo-cher
                                Pax Frank
                                Matteo De Cristofaro
                                Meo
                                Boyarde Roneen
                                wastrel
                                Drew Kerrigan
                                Jordan Wood
                                Kasey Patrick Morgan
                                Callum Love
                                Petrichor "petrak@7604"
                                Devon Cupo
                                Big Simple
                                Kevin Orren
                                Lennart Schefe
                                Beemancer
                                Lady Eithné, Queen of Brokilon
                                Nic Gard
                                NeroPrime
                                InfiniteTidalWave
                                Aveon Zero
                                Joshua Southerland
                                _tr
                                James Earle
                                Nick Correale
                                MichaÅ‚ Byczko                                
                                Reuben Eadon
                                Shane Allcroft
                                Aidan Page
                                Earthly Delights Ogdo
                                John Szevin
                                Shane Allcroft
                                Kelly Joyce
                                Cleo Lamb
                                Mike Sipior
                                James Canter
                                Joshua Buckley
                                Qingyao Sun
                                CHOWARD
                                Luke J.
                                Gobi Silverfrog, siver and gold goddess
                                Ethan Rigby
                                Ethan "Kobold" CB
                                Maria Ross Colton Chamberlin
                                {{w-W-Y-Y-Y-Y-Y-W-w sequence|Paingouin}} "Jordan B."
                                James Lagervall
                                Doug "Severian" Callahan
                                Leo Durante
                                Rarden
                                Ray ({{r|books}})
                                awful_falafel
                                ambersand
                                dmajorduckie
                                Lukas Wagner (König Muskelmagen)
                                Marek Pohlodek
                                Kamille Rose
                                Retes;Nome
                                Sabboth Ochoa
                                Almea
                                Caleb Ulichney
                                Visnex
                                CreativeCorpse
                                Kelly Vincent
                                Teagan Erika Stephanie Strickland
                                Mirthful Sloth
                                beepy roboticvenusian (enchiridion)
                                AvianAnarchy
                                Gavin Conover

  ]]
</topic>
  <topic name="Open Source Licenses" DisplayName="▶Open Source Licenses">▶
[[{{c|License for Harmony (https://github.com/pardeike/Harmony)}}
  {{W|MIT License}}

  Copyright (c) 2017 Andreas Pardeike

{{c|License for FuzzySharp (https://github.com/JakeBayer/FuzzySharp)}}
  {{W|MIT License}}

  Copyright (c) 2018 
  
{{c|License for UnityStandaloneFileBrowser
 (https://github.com/gkngkc/UnityStandaloneFileBrowser)}}
  {{W|MIT License}}

  Copyright (c) 2017 Gökhan Gökçe

{{c|License for ZString (https://github.com/Cysharp/ZString)}}
  {{W|MIT License}}

  Copyright (c) 2020 Yoshifumi Kawai / Cysharp, Inc.

{{c|License for UniTask (https://github.com/Cysharp/UniTask)}}
  {{W|MIT License}}

  Copyright (c) 2019 Yoshifumi Kawai / Cysharp, Inc.


{{W|MIT License}} {{c|- Full Text}}
  Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy
  of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"), to deal
  in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights
  to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell
  copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is
  furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

  The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in all
  copies or substantial portions of the Software.

  THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
  IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
  FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
  AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
  LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM,
  OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE
  SOFTWARE.]]

</topic>
</help>