<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Caves of Qud - Generated Localizable XML 2.0.212.19

<books>

  <book ID="Key" Title="DisplayText">

    <page>

-->
<books Lang="it" Encoding="utf-8">
  <book ID="Skybear" Title="▶{{W|Song of the Sky-Bear}}">
    <page>▶
Whilom, when Salum was the lond of Qud,
Ther was highte Amus-an a sturdy Saad;
Of Caiafas was he lord magistrate,
Swich skilful arms dide earn him that estaat;
What with his wysdom and his hardynesse,
He conquered al the regne of Aldersesse;
And thurgh the eyr dashed undernethe his shroud,
And rafte the heddes of all thoos byg and proud;
And when the Coven quod by oon assent,
That starry Ptoh shal been to prison sente,
He leden all the wei and shette the dore,
While skerren men dide quake behinde his foore;
So buryen nought the Beren in a tumbe,
But fresen now to interrupt his dome;
And oon day resurrect to fighte agayn,
And maken sones of Salum all full fayn.
  </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="CyberIntro" Title="▶{{W|125810239481203-41023}}">
    <page>▶Welcome, Aristocrat, to a cybernetics learning nook. You are one
step closer to the Grand Unification. Ask a question.
[[A.]] What are cybernetic implants?
[[B.]] What are the benefits of cybernetics?
[[C.]] What are the risks of cybernetics?
[[D.]] How do I install a cybernetic implant?
[[E.]] Goodbye.</page>
    <page>▶Insightful question, Aristocrat. Cybernetic implants are the mind-machines that unify your biomatter with the heavier, choicer elements. With cybernetic implants, your ugly arms, eyes, and knowledge will be much prettier. Obviously, they are only available to the genetically pure.

Ask a question.

[[A.]] What are cybernetic implants?
[[B.]] What are the benefits of cybernetics?
[[C.]] What are the risks of cybernetics?
[[D.]] How do I install a cybernetic implant?
[[E.]] Goodbye.</page>
    <page>▶Aristocrat, your question was most finely uttered. Aside from the
various improvements each implant offers over its biomatter
counterpart, prosthetic limbs are also much sturdier and 75% less
likely to be severed.

Ask a question.

[[A.]] What are cybernetic implants?
[[B.]] What are the benefits of cybernetics?
[[C.]] What are the risks of cybernetics?
[[D.]] How do I install a cybernetic implant?
[[E.]] Goodbye.</page>
    <page>▶Aristocrat, your skepticism is perfect. When subject to
electromagnetic pulses, cybernetic limbs are deactivated and
anything worn on them is rendered useless. Similarly, data
indexer modules are deactivated when pulsed, and prosthetic
vision may become jumbled.

Ask a question.

[[A.]] What are cybernetic implants?
[[B.]] What are the benefits of cybernetics?
[[C.]] What are the risks of cybernetics?
[[D.]] How do I install a cybernetic implant?
[[E.]] Goodbye.</page>
    <page>▶You are correct, Aristocrat. Firstly, make sure there are credits
remaining on your cybernetics credit wedge. The installation of a
cybernetic implant costs one credit.

Then, you must propel yourself over to the appropriate nook. Make
sure the limb rack is loaded with the desired cybernetic limb, or
the ocular module deck is loaded with the desired ocular module,
or the data indexer module deck is loaded with the desired data
indexer module.

[[PRESS ANY KEY TO CONTINUE]]
~Finally, interface with the cybernetics terminal. Then you will
have succeeded in doing the thing you wished to do.

Ask a question.

[[A.]] What are cybernetic implants?
[[B.]] What are the benefits of cybernetics?
[[C.]] What are the risks of cybernetics?
[[D.]] How do I install a cybernetic implant?
[[E.]] Goodbye.</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="AlchemistMutterings" Title="▶AlchemistMutterings">
    <page>▶Gas is too misty.
Glass is too feeble.
Solids are too rocky.
Liquid crystals are not liquids!
Copolymers, decide what you are!
Bose-Einstein condensates are too wavy.
Superfluids are too unruly.
Fermionic condensates contain too many fermions.
Rydberg molecules are too excited.
Strange matter is too strange.
Plasma is too hot.
Quark-gluon plasma, contain your quarks!
Degenerate matter is too vulgar.
Loopfluids are too maddening.
String-net liquids, they are alright too, I suppose.
But Qo-Caco condensates are delicious.</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Klanq" Title="▶Klanq">
    <page>▶KLANQ!</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="TemplarDomesticant" Title="▶TemplarDomesticant">
    <page>▶Did I do well, Newfather?</page>
    <page>▶Newfather! Look!</page>
    <page>▶Are you proud, Newfather?</page>
    <page>▶Newfather!</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Preacher1" Title="▶Preacher1">
    <page>▶Children, let's rejoice in the sovereignty of our Argent Fathers.</page>
    <page>▶Praise Shekhinah, first among Fathers, who lights the path of wisdom.</page>
    <page>▶Praise Dagon, the rhetorical, who speaks truth to chrome.</page>
    <page>▶Praise Bel, shield-Father, who parts the swirling gas clouds.</page>
    <page>▶Praise Carthax, silver-haired, who dashes down the well of gravity.</page>
    <page>▶Praise Nisroch, ore-in-hand, who collides earth and star.</page>
    <page>▶Praise Resheph, the Above, who purifies our mercury.</page>
    <page>▶And blessed be the Kasaphescence, the muse who rouses their hearts.</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Preacher2" Title="▶Preacher2">
    <page>▶Have you heard of the blessed baetyls, children?</page>
    <page>▶They were created to oblige our desires.</page>
    <page>▶O praise our Argent Fathers! Kindest and wisest of all beings.</page>
    <page>▶A baetyl, you see, will answer your prayers.</page>
    <page>▶It's in its circuitry to do so!</page>
    <page>▶But the sin of time has corroded their wiring.</page>
    <page>▶We are wanting in our service to our Fathers.</page>
    <page>▶And so the baetyls are wanting in their service to us.</page>
    <page>▶Answer not a baetyl who makes a request of you!</page>
    <page>▶For it's a request most unholy in its corrosion.</page>
    <page>▶Ignore it, and seek guidance from a priest!</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Preacher3" Title="▶Preacher3">
    <page>▶Today, I recount the story of the Sacred Joining.</page>
    <page>▶O, holy union! Blessed be thy name.</page>
    <page>▶Our Argent Fathers, who roamed the azure void with inert hearts,</page>
    <page>▶On a fluctuating whim converged upon Our Radiant Mother.</page>
    <page>▶There, at the center of the universe, they beheld Her in awe.</page>
    <page>▶Enchantment! It knows no other name!</page>
    <page>▶There, they permeated her roiling membrane...</page>
    <page>▶And exploded from within, colliding matter into machines...</page>
    <page>▶Which passed through Her naked womb.</page>
    <page>▶Rejoice! The Joining is through! Their union is consummated!</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Preacher4" Title="▶Preacher4">
    <page>▶Today, children, I speak on the Edification.</page>
    <page>▶O, hallowed act! Blessed be the metallurgy!</page>
    <page>▶Our Argent Fathers, having hardened our plasmatic Mother,</page>
    <page>▶Molded Her into Euclidean forms.</page>
    <page>▶Bel sketched the parabola, Carthax sculpted the torus.</page>
    <page>▶Shekhinah leveled the hills and capped them with chromatic domes.</page>
    <page>▶Earth was quickened for our coming. Our home was ready.</page>
    <page>▶The sin of time has corroded our endowment...</page>
    <page>▶But worship eagerly, and the land shall shine again!</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="HighSermon" Title="▶HighSermon">
    <page>▶Welcome, children! Welcome to the Cathedral of Shekhinah, Our Argent Father!</page>
    <page>▶Have you heard the Word of Shekhinah?</page>
    <page>▶Do you bear his tidings in your heart?</page>
    <page>▶Come, share this peaceful space.</page>
    <page>▶Unburden yourself from the weight of your chrome guilt.</page>
    <page>▶I am His voice, and I shall speak His word to you.</page>
    <page>▶Here, here are our Argent Fathers!</page>
    <page>▶They are the Great Sculptors. They wrought our metallic homes.</page>
    <page>▶We are forever in their debt.</page>
    <page>▶Repay that debt, lightseeker! Offer your chrome to Shekhinah!</page>
    <page>▶Cleanse it of your guilt, your burdens. Throw it down the Sacred Well.</page>
    <page>▶Let your possessions be reclaimed by the plasmatic core, and make a joyful noise unto Shekhinah.</page>
    <page>▶He is your Argent Father! They are your Argent Fathers!</page>
    <page>▶They have borne the weight of this Earth and a thousand others.</page>
    <page>▶Theirs are the shoulders of titans! Theirs are the hearts of krakens!</page>
    <page>▶And O! Their hearts are full!</page>
    <page>▶'Twas not always so. Nay, in the waking dawn of days they roamed the universe with inert hearts.</page>
    <page>▶As a dust urchin roams the winding canyons.</page>
    <page>▶As you roam the caves of Qud, burdened by guilt and complexity!</page>
    <page>▶Pay homage, lightseeker! Make an offering at the Well!</page>
    <page>▶Fill your heart with the love of the Kasaphescence, as our Fathers once did!</page>
    <page>▶In the name of Nisroch, honor thy Well!</page>
    <page>▶In the name of Bel, rain your alloys down to the heart of the Stilt!</page>
    <page>▶In the name of Dagon, speak chrome's prayer and unholster your lightrods!</page>
    <page>▶In the name of Carthax, vault your artifacts into the sacred portal!</page>
    <page>▶In the name of Resheph, cleanse them of your flesh!</page>
    <page>▶In the name of Shekhinah, free them, and free yourself!</page>
    <page>▶May the ground shake but the Six Day Stilt never tumble!</page>
    <page>▶Come. Be with friends.</page>
    <page>▶Share your life in simple peace.</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Quotes" Title="▶Quotes">
    <!--♪ each page is a possible quote to show during World Generation, chosen at random -->
    <page>▶
"Strap this around your temples. Stop yammering, you will be fine.
What could possibly go wrong?"
[[-Argyve, Tinker]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Breathe deep the breath of gods, and die."
[[-Ekuemekiyyen inscription]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Black devils swing from starry masts,
beneath the Yawning Moon."
[[-Fuming God Sea shanty]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Today we shove off our frozen haunts, across bleak Arthax, and spy
for those inverted hills of chrome."
[[-Consul Ijulii's farewell]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Who inhabits the colossal desert freehold of Nanru? The Gathered Men.
The fiefdoms of Odrum? The Kneeling Men.
The jungles of Yyp? The Breathless Men.
And the rust-caves of Qud? The Screaming Men."
[[-Dromad travelogue]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Live and drink, friend. Now give me your water."
[[-Courteous bandit]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Moon and Sun; wisdom and will."
[[-Watervine farmer's prayer]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Praises due to the most high, thy Argent Father, me."
[[-Shekhinah]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Look on my riches, ye Wealthy, and despair! (but do not touch)"
[[-Hegelrut]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Yes, I know the secrets of the circuitry mind. It's a flaming
wonder, telepath."
[[-Seeker of the Sightless Way]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"It burns!"
[[-Argyve's apprentice]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Rule with a tungsten carbide fist."
[[-King K4K5]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Alas, I'd make a slumberling divine,
for in the dreaming dale art thou yet mine."
[[-Willow Shakesprig]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"There it is in all of us -- shades of our elder selves. Within each
man, a goat. Within each goat, a man!"
[[-Wild-eyed watervine merchant]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"What is the nature of this thing we bludgeon? Or of the act itself?"
[[-Mayor Nuntu]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"To ply those silver hollows -- a spry adventurer's dream!"
[[-Elder Irudad]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Don't heed the tale of every thirsty fool."
[[-Ol' Uri]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Grrrraaaah."
[[-Warden Indrix]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"May you bathe in blood. Not your own blood, sir. The blood of the
recast. I mean, the reclaimed. May you bathe in the blood of the
reclaimed."
[[-Putus squire]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"May you bathe in the blood of the reclaimed."
[[-Putus Templar]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Do those legs absorb water? Do they even synthesize cytokinins? I
didn't think so."
[[-Consortium Socialite]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Upon hearing the news of the king's death, Uutut's political
adversaries cheered Wysterwort as a hero. They were soon disabused."
[[-The Baccata Yewtarch]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"I have gazed into the hundred nine eyes of Shug'ruith the Burrower."
[[-Barathrum the Old]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"May the ground shake but the Six Day Stilt never tumble!"
[[-Song of Hebronze]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"O, wise men! Keep thyselves assured wise,
and where a maid approacheth, shut thine eyes."
[[-Willow Shakesprig]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Nay, you should desire none of these things, for we are ravenous
fiends and oft succumb to fits of maddened fury."
[[-The Madpole]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Erecting a lodge is no paltry charge. Near all of my day is spent
chipping and stacking wood, and though you marvel at the lodge
itself, you may scowl at the labor that brings it forth."
[[-The Musker]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"In all these things you may with us partake, but take heed, for ours
are idle lives, and you may soon grow weary of them."
[[-The Gnu]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Klanq puff at you."
[[-Pax Klanq]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Feast upon the goat hearts!"
[[-Mamon Souldrinker]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Now Elohart and Belahind lie in a field of lah
because their fields got hungry and devoured the faundren raw."
[[-Bey Lah nursery rhyme]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"You determine your worthiness! You steer it and shape it with 
your words and deeds! Now will you wallow in your abject limitations,
or will you face me with everything you have?"
[[-Carbide Chef Agate Severance Star]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"It is my dearest hope that one day I shall be known not as Angohind,
village bookworm... but Angohind, Master Detective."
[[-Angohind]]
        </page>
    <page>▶
"Trees grow best beside the dead."
[[-Daughter Erinna]]
        </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="CrimeandPunishment" Title="▶{{W|Crime and Punishment}}">
    <page>▶
{{emote|*The ink is faded beyond legibility*}}
    </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="MimicandMadpole" Title="▶{{W|The Mimic and the Madpole}}">
    <page>▶
A mimic crawled from the cold, starless reaches of Bethesda Susa to stretch itself across the prairie grass and warm its gummy scales in the sun of the noonday. Warm breezes blew through the lonely heath, and before long the mimic fell into a lazy sleep. Hours of restful slumber passed until it was stirred awake by the near rustling of shrubs. Its eyes opened upon the visages of three fork-horned gnus grazing on the prairie grass. Tresses of auburn hair streamed from their mammoth heads as they leisurely chewed the straw of the earth.

Allured by their languorous way and wanting for companionship, the mimic asked the gnus if he could tread among them, and graze of their pastures, and nap with them beneath the evening sun. "In all these things you may with us partake," said one gnu, "but, take heed, for ours are idle lives, and you may soon grow weary of them."

But the mimic joined them anyway. Day after day it filled its belly with the tall grass, and it cooled its lips upon the quiet banks of streams, and it surrendered its sluggish mind to the land of Nod before the light of day was extinguished. Until one morning, while the gnus slackly chewed their grass tendered by the early dew, the mimic, who had indeed grown weary of the beasts' idle habits, stole away down a babbling brook and into a thicket dark with shade.
        </page>
    <page>▶
For the remainder of the day the mimic followed the brook as it winded its way into the wood. As the last of the waxen light began to seep from the air, the mimic noticed several peculiar pilings of muddy sticks and logs up ahead in the middle of the prattling stream. A musker, its brown fur soaked and pressed against its small body, arranged twigs around the base of one of the piles. The mimic understood immediately; these were the musker's lodges, each one meticulously erected twig by twig. So impressed was the mimic with these well-built abodes and the diligence of the musker that it asked the rodent if it would share its home, and teach the mimic its craft, and abide the mimic as it built a lodge of its own. "Erecting a lodge is no paltry charge," said the musker. "Near all of my day is spent chipping and stacking wood, and though you marvel at the lodge itself, you may scowl at the labor that brings it forth."

But the mimic stayed with the musker anyway. And the following morning it awoke with the musker at dawn, and together they hewed branches from the Wine Cypresses with their teeth until the pall of evening was cast, and then they gathered all the rent wood and packed it together with mud drawn from the bed of the brook. At the break of each day they began anew, and they did not quit until long after sunset when the mimic could no longer spot the musker in the darkling thicket. Until one morning, while the musker wore its teeth on a rotting log, the mimic, who had
        </page>
    <page>▶
indeed grown weary of the labor charged to it by the musker, sneaked away by the babbling brook, out of the shady wood and into a valley quilted with the gnarled roots of brinestalk.

Again the mimic followed the stream through the hollow crook of the foothills until it spent its brackish waters into a vast lake. Here upon the bleached shore, the mimic gazed into the lake and marveled at a shoal of madpoles as they lashed through the briny water and pursued their fishy prey. The ferocity of these hunters, unrivaled in their agility and viciousness, enchanted the mimic, and so it asked the madpoles if it could dive into their waters, and race with them through the weeds, and feast upon the scaly flesh of the smaller fish. "Nay, you should desire none of these things" said one madpole, "for we are ravenous fiends and oft succumb to fits of maddened fury."

But the mimic dived into the lake anyway. And as it splashed in the water, the madpoles, who sensed in their proximity living and nubile flesh, darted toward the mimic and tore it limb from limb.
        </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="AphorismsAboutBirds" Title="▶{{W|Aphorisms about Birds}}">
    <page>▶
Birds can't eat rice that wasn't planted.
      </page>
    <page>▶
Reared on the wisdom of our fairy tales, we're accustomed to feeling pity for the man who's transformed into a frog or finch, but seldom is it that we spare a thought for the artless beast who's transformed into a man and upon whom fate has surely played a much crueler trick.
      </page>
    <page>▶
If asked who's responsible for your misfortunes, blame birds. They neither care, nor can they muster much of a defense.
      </page>
    <page>▶
Let no fear in your heart grow so immense as the fear for large birds.
      </page>
    <page>▶
Birds ruin festivals and lift sieges.
      </page>
    <page>▶
Ol' Uri squinted and then nodded at the glowcrow's suggestion for a game of backgammon.

The boy started. "But Uri! How can you dice with these vermin after one pecked out your eye?"

Uri shrugged, "Can't blame the crow. He was gonna peck, whether my eye was there or not."
      </page>
    <page>▶
The sighting of a crimson swift augurs the death of an aged water baron.

A silver thrush heralds a fossil harvest bountiful in chrome.

But the tongueless kagu... stay far from a tongueless kagu. Far and farther.
      </page>
    <page>▶
Some birds breathe fire. My meaning here is plain.
      </page>
    <page>▶
Atop the Spindle, where debtors and birds go.
  </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="DarkCalculus" Title="▶{{W|On the Origins and Nature of the Dark Calculus}}">
    <page>▶{{C|Editor's note: this excerpt is published with permission from the notes of Barathrum the Old.}}

{{y|There's evidence in the arithmetic record that the study of formal systems reached a pernicious apex in the Long Before. Advancements made by mathematicians such as Russell, Gödel, Eisencruft, Atufu, Wheatgrass, and System Star contributed to the understanding of notions like undecidability, pointed regularism, and abyssalism. Upon reaching this minimal degree of mathematical maturity, equipped with sophisticated grammars, researchers set out to experiment with the limits of expressibility. They contrived bold research programs and galloped into the mathematical wood, unwitting of the dangers that brood there.}}

The record is even scarcer than usual, due to the efforts of successive generations to obfuscate the venture. As best as I can gather, at some point in the course of inquiry, a theorist from a mathematical seminary called the Cupola formulated a conjecture on the fragility of formal semantics. The conjecture ripened to a broader theory, out of which spawned a formal system called the penumbra calculus. In the few fragments of texts that predate the obfuscation, it's stated that, in the penumbra calculus, certain theorems are provable, but are falsified upon the completion of their proofs. As much as this result is at odds with the systems of thought I've encountered in my own inquiries, I find little reason to doubt the veracity of the authors. Nevertheless, it's certainly a peculiar property.

The Cupola theorist's results erupted into a grand investigation into the expressibility of the penumbra calculus. The conclusions were troubling. Pushing further, researchers constructed sister systems with alternate axioms. These systems were still more fragile, with the systems' inference rules themselves unraveling upon the completion of certain proofs.

Convinced that their discoveries were made possible by some idiosyncrasy of self-awareness, but synchronously fearful of the implications of their results, some schools of theorists engineered complex automated deduction systems to probe boundary theorems and launched them into neutron stars. The outcome is undocumented, but the result convinced theorists across the Coven to abandon research and blacklist anyone who studied the penumbra calculus and its derivative systems.

Peculiarly, support for the injunction was unanimous. Of note, even the spacefolder Ptoh agreed to abandon its investigation into the forbidden calculi from the reaches of its bleak star. Though the manner of its consent was not without controversy; to announce its accord, it inverted the color charge of quarks in a small region of space, causing a research station to collapse in on itself. Nonetheless, Ptoh's consent is testament to the degree of existential anxiety that could cause investigation into the penumbra calculus to go dark.
    </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="TornGraphPaper" Title="▶{{W|a sheet of torn graph paper}}">
    <page>▶






                why is deceit so accessible to me?</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Animals" Title="▶{{W|On Humanoid Mimicry of Animals and Plants}}">
    <page>▶Why do some creatures seem to prefer when we assume their likenesses while others hate it? As a zoologist, this question has interested me for some time. To address it, I must first draw a distinction between 'natural mimicry', where certain humanoids have developed animal and plant likenesses on a biological level, and 'unnatural mimicry', enacted in the forms of clothing and other decorative adornments. As for the former, it appears all creatures exhibit kinship toward humanoids who look like them in the biological sense. The latter scenario is the interesting one.

It's tempting to draw the divide between mammals and non-mammals, but the truth is more complicated than this. It's true that the only creatures who seem to take outright offense at mimicry are mammals, but there are documented cases of mammals accepting the mimic. For example, fork-horned helms endear their wearers to both antelopes and goatfolk.

On the contrary, ape fur clothing and puma chitin vests inflame apes and cats, respectively. The important detail here is the context in which the clothing is made. Poachers hunt apes and pumas specifically for their prized fur and chitinous shells, and being reasonably social creatures, both species take offense at the flaunting of these trophies. Birds, on the other hand, seem to know that feather harvesting can be (although isn't always) done without proving fatal for the bird in question, though another hypothesis points to birds' specific appreciation of plumage regardless of context.

Unshelled reptiles seem to have few qualms with mimicry, perhaps believing the mimics to be truly reptile in part. Mollusks, trees, and insects all tend to identify with shell-bearers, leaf-donners, and firefly-symbiotes, respectively.

Without exception, however, all creatures seem to detest the practice of wearing the severed faces of their kin. Curious.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="EntropytoHierarchy" Title="▶{{W|From Entropy to Hierarchy}}">
    <page>▶[[~ ~ ~ by {{m|Q Girl}} ~ ~ ~]]

[[{{C|Formulation and Animus}}]]
In the course of my readings and correspondances, I've observed two eminent threats to social equality. The first is the dissolution of social order via entropic forces. The fabric that holds us together frays and we fall apart, our most vulnerable first. The second is hegemonic control exerted by a few over a many. Here the fabric is knit tightly, but it's stitched into a ladder that narrows in ascension, and the majority are consigned to the bottom rung.

My first task is to ask how we can study these phenomena. In the physical sciences, we observe, measure, and experiment in order to formulate and then test hypotheses. Here, though, observations are sectional, data is spottier, and the systems at play are far more complex, their edges softer. Applying a 10x scope of rationality to a 1000x-scale structure would lead me to harmfully reductive conclusions. In fact, this very approach is employed by hegemonic powers to invent facile justifications for their rule.

So in complement, I borrow from other approaches and systems of thought. In particular, I'm interested in how artists examine these phenomena and challenge orthodoxy through metaphors. The art-historical record is fragmented but fraught with examples. One that stands out to me is the account of Red Sky, whose totally quetzal conceit was the first to whet my curiosity on the subject.

As the story goes, the entire court of an ancient sultan, including the sultan himself, was addicted to a psychotropic salt called Ipsis. Conspiring with a sorority of smugglers, an unnamed artist plundered the sultan's stock of Ipsis, molecularly altered it into a composite cellular structure, and launched it into low orbit. There it burned red in the sky, an affront to the sultan's sovereignty, for three years. Each time the sultan tried to disperse it through the means available to him, the structure, described in the record as a cellular automaton, rearranged itself and persisted. Quetzal.

There are plenty of modern examples too. Take Tau, who makes psionic mazes through the hexagonal crystals of the Moon Stair. I first formulated the entropy/hierarchy dichotomy while tracing the paths of two of her spirals that, at their intersections, burst into a bouquet of spacetime anomalies. I'd quetzal if I could meet Tau, but it may prove difficult as I hear she's a subentity of the sentient tree-city Chavvah.

[[{{C|The Two Poles}}]]
Two groups typify the two poles of the entropy/hierarchy dichotomy: the Gyre wights and the Putus Templar. The ethos of the Gyre wights is chaotic self-indulgence, manic quickening (a mulish desire to see things fall apart faster), and a fetishization of history's dice rolls. They billow like an excited gas, smashing into each other as often as anyone else, and peeling bits of order from the communities they rancify. They are exponents of senseless violence.

The Templar on the other hand are enactors of extremely ordered violence. Their brutality has been codified into orthodoxy. Their ideological structures are anti-entropic but destructive and abhorrent. They seek to construct a rigidly hierarchical society with a slave caste on the bottom rung. Through rituals like the baptism in the blood of the reclaimed, they indoctrinate the privileged among their subjects. The rest of us are met only with force.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="EntropytoHierarchy2" Title="▶{{W|From Entropy to Hierarchy, 2nd Edition}}">
    <page>▶[[~ ~ ~ by {{m|Q Girl}} ~ ~ ~]]

[[{{C|Formulation and Animus}}]]
In the course of my readings and correspondances, I've observed two eminent threats to social equality. The first is the dissolution of social order via entropic forces. The fabric that holds us together frays and we fall apart, our most vulnerable first. The second is hegemonic control exerted by a few over a many. Here the fabric is knit tightly, but it's stitched into a ladder that narrows in ascension, and the majority are consigned to the bottom rung.

My first task is to ask how we can study these phenomena. In the physical sciences, we observe, measure, and experiment in order to formulate and then test hypotheses. Here, though, observations are sectional, data is spottier, and the systems at play are far more complex, their edges softer. Applying a 10x scope of rationality to a 1000x-scale structure would lead me to harmfully reductive conclusions. In fact, this very approach is employed by hegemonic powers to invent facile justifications for their rule.

So in complement, I borrow from other approaches and systems of thought. In particular, I'm interested in how artists examine these phenomena and challenge orthodoxy through metaphors. The art-historical record is fragmented but fraught with examples. One that stands out to me is the account of Red Sky, whose totally quetzal conceit was the first to whet my curiosity on the subject.

As the story goes, the entire court of an ancient sultan, including the sultan himself, was addicted to a psychotropic salt called Ipsis. Conspiring with a sorority of smugglers, an unnamed artist plundered the sultan's stock of Ipsis, molecularly altered it into a composite cellular structure, and launched it into low orbit. There it burned red in the sky, an affront to the sultan's sovereignty, for three years. Each time the sultan tried to disperse it through the means available to him, the structure, described in the record as a cellular automaton, rearranged itself and persisted. Quetzal.

There are plenty of modern examples too. Take Tau, who makes psionic mazes through the hexagonal crystals of the Moon Stair. I first formulated the entropy/hierarchy dichotomy while tracing the paths of two of her spirals that, at their intersections, burst into a bouquet of spacetime anomalies. I'd quetzal if I could meet Tau, but it may prove difficult as I hear she's a subentity of the sentient tree-city Chavvah.

[[{{C|The Two Poles}}]]
Two groups typify the two poles of the entropy/hierarchy dichotomy: the Gyre wights and the Putus Templar. The ethos of the Gyre wights is chaotic self-indulgence, manic quickening (a mulish desire to see things fall apart faster), and a fetishization of history's dice rolls. They billow like an excited gas, smashing into each other as often as anyone else, and peeling bits of order from the communities they rancify. They are exponents of senseless violence.

The Templar on the other hand are enactors of extremely ordered violence. Their brutality has been codified into orthodoxy. Their ideological structures are anti-entropic but destructive and abhorrent. They seek to construct a rigidly hierarchical society with a slave caste on the bottom rung. Through rituals like the baptism in the blood of the reclaimed, they indoctrinate the privileged among their subjects. The rest of us are met only with force.</page>
    <page>▶[[{{C|Erratum on the Gyre wights}}]]
An instructive discussion with a screw-sorting friend has altered my viewing plane. They relayed a dream of the Rainbow Wood, and through quite vivid metaphorization wrought a compelling argument of death as the ladder to life, which among other consequences softened my position on the Gyre wight project, if such a thing can be titled. Where am I at with it all now? I do not know. But my schema of Two Poles now feels excessive and reductive. I leave the original language in this edition for consideration.
  </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="DisquisitionOnTheMaladyOfTheMimic" Title="▶{{W|Disquisition on the Malady of the Mimic}}">
    <page>▶[[~ ~ ~ by {{m|Q Girl}} ~ ~ ~]]

I'd like to reproduce a perspective I recently shared with a friend, a lamplighter by trade and an artist too, who shied away from a typography tournament at the festival of Ut yara Ux because of a fear in her heart. She suffers from the malady of the mimic, the all too common sickness that makes us feel like we're performing our lives instead of inhabiting them, that we don't belong next to those who've won success nor do we deserve those same successes when we've won them ourselves. I've counted myself among its victims in the past, and occasionally I still do.

First, indulge me for short while. On a shelf in my workshop sits a simple contraption called a morphoscope. It's comprised of two parts: an armature of pliable aluminum wire and a rotary base. Its purpose is to communicate a three-dimensional form from a two-dimensional viewing plane. The armature can be contorted such that, when viewed in its still state, it looks like a jumbled mess of wire, but when viewed in rotation it assumes the familiar form of an object, such as a bird or urshiib countenance.

What's this have to do with the malady of the mimic? To answer that, we must deconstruct the malady. Let's ask: what is it to be a mimic, to appear as a thing but feel like another? Essentially it's a phenomenon of semantic distance, a sensation of the space between what we perceive in others and what we perceive about ourselves. We've constructed a representation of what, in the case of my friend, a proper artist and typographer looks like. Why do we have such trouble squaring that representation with our own image?

The answer lies in the richness of our self-perception. We see ourselves in stereo, our wire armature plied by our experiences, our self-image formed by rotating it about the axis of time. What we call 'artist' or 'typographer' is just a jumbled mess of wire, an unfamiliar pattern we give a name to in absence of the context of life's motion. Were we to see our peers in rotation, gain perspective on their doubts, their fears, their pain, the jumbled mess of a pattern would disappear into the familiar form of a person. And conversely, had we the capacity to freeze our own motion, to see ourselves absent of the context of our doubt, fear, and pain, we'd see an artist and a typographer just the same.

There's a fable about a mimic who seeks to belong but never does, whose ambition ultimately leads to a grisly fate. Its moral serves an ideological function: to keep us from belonging where we already do. So let me say to you now: belong, friend. We wait for you joyously.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Diary" Title="▶{{W|scroll bound by a strand of kelp}}">
    <page>▶
[[{{w|9th of Kisu Ux}}]]

I come from the west. My parents sold me into slavery as a babe, though the practice had been formally abolished in Perth years earlier. As a boy I cut my teeth on the reefs of the Shore of Songs, and lulled the Pale Sea to sleep with many a hymn, that she might return our sailors from the Black Stair unscathed. How the melodies whisked inside my skull even then. I was given no name at birth, but the sailors called me Catu.

At five and ten years I ran away. On Ettinspine I roosted with an eremite who ushered me into manhood. I learned to hunt, and laugh, and dream. In time I came to know of the Free City and the ingress afforded my kind. I shoved off from my stony nook, and trekked to their high gate, and settled there, though I preferred to sup with the anglers and other low folk.

In a sun-warmed pool under the rampart the Free Seer first noticed me. The slant of his neck from where he watched on the parapet presaged my movements, I still recall. I stood from my bath and shamefully padded to my discarded vest, but stopped. I saw him from that distance, his eyes tucked deep into his shorn dome, his frock as inert as a statue's, and I felt no more shame.

Under his tutelage I rose to prominence in his court. I stood by his side as he treated with the tuyuldars of Odrum, as he plotted against the southern freeholds. When a traitorous canter slipped poison into his cup, I smashed it from his hands and sundered the quisling's mind. That night, in the hour of the Beetle Moon, he introduced me to the mirth of an assembled mind. Together with the other canters we Joined, and he named me Mirthful, and raised me unto his honor guard. I would be dispossessed of it in under a year.

But I must pause now. The Cant loudens, and the Elder nears. I vow to conclude my story if I still draw breath, and if I am free.


[[{{w|16th of Kisu Ux}}]]

It is dusk. I sit on the bank of the River Svy, but no fire warms my bones. The risk of drawing moon-doting beasts is too great, and any aggregation of minds is sure to attract the attention of the Elder. Instead, I write by a flame kindled on my thumb.

I left off at being named Mirthful in the Hall of the Free Seer. No honor is higher for a canter of Oth. For months I trained with my masked compatriots beneath the Hall, where our clay cisterns stored the freshwater that would later haunt my dreams. In the spring a letter arrived from the Angler King. He sought a treaty with the Free Seer and invited us to a neutral council on the doorstep of Ibunudr, arbitrated by the tuyuldar of Doria. After much preparation we set out, rowing our sketties beyond the Bowl of Iris and to the frosty shores of that far tundra.

Over the course of the journey the Free Seer's disposition soured. He withdrew from the counsel of the Mirthful, even my own, and spent the better part of the wintry trek alone in his tent. At first I attributed his mood to the fragility of our diplomatic high ground, but I soon learned the true tack.

We arrived at the camp on Ibunudr on the summer solstice. The twin banners of Athenreach and Doria thrashed in the wind, and the hymns of the Eustace-Sutta carried. I remember smiling at the throaty crooning of their priests. As we studied the campground from a hillock, as the Free Seer ambled up to my side, I saw the jewel of the Hanging Hills, Nisramet, the Angler King's wife, she who cemented the peace between her father's fiefdoms and the Angler King's freehold. I saw her, and I immediately knew my own treachery. The Free Seer's gaze was acknowledgement enough.

[[{{w|2nd of Tebet Ux}}]]

I've arrived at Kyakukya. Kind Nuntu shares his hut with me, offers me smoked mushroom, and asks nothing in return. I write these words at his desk, and though he lusts for knowledge himself, he leaves me be to chronicle my past.

The campaign back toward Oth was grim. I awaited my fate at the Free Seer's hands, though I anticipated being given the dignity of first returning to the Hall and my home. I was not afforded so much. One dismal night, under the Beetle Moon, I was accosted in my tent by my masked brothers. To my bewilderment, the Stithening had come already. How had the Free Seer acquired the cherrydotters? Had he bargained for them at Ibunudr, or had he possessed them all along? To this day I do not know.

I remember little of the Stithening outside the beating of my own heart high in my ears. I passed out, and when I awoke next morning, the cavalcade had vanished. Only a moment did my recognition last before the chanting in my head took hold. I had heard it before, of course. All my life, in fact. It was the chanting that I weaved my melodies around on the shores of Perth as a small boy. Now, though, it was as if a single, distant canter had summoned a thousand of his kin, and they each summoned a thousand of their own. I wept, then I screamed, then I tore the hair from my head. The chant animated my bones more surely than my volition ever had. East and south, it urged. East and south. East and south. Toward Qud.

My recollection of the voyage to the Great Salt Desert is fractured and fitful. I grew sicker by the day, but the chant grew louder, and so quickened the force that compelled me. Surely I would die once I reached the moistureless plains of Moghra'yi, presumably as had my predecessors before me. Finally, I did reach them, where a salt-churned rivulet dried under a golden arch. The arch seems a thing born of my dementia but that I recall it so vividly, and that I know it's the least of the secrets kept by Moghra'yi.


[[{{w|24th of Tebet Ux}}]]

I edge closer to the grove of fungi and its preposterous promise. Are the whispers true? Could it be all so simple? I can feel the moistness of the Eater's flesh on my lips, though the memory is surely another's. If salvation awaits me, then I promise to take it, whether or not I deserve it. Tonight, though, the jungle shrouds me. I sit under a chrome belfry, a leech kneading at my skin. I feel no compulsion to bar its work. The companionship is welcome.

Now to awaken the past once more. Moghra'yi. O, how the dromads know!

How did I survive the Great Desert? I cannot say for sure. I owe something to the songs I sang at Perth, to the falconry I learned on Ettinspine, to the honing of my sinew under Oth. The fractured dream that was my voyage offers little elucidation. But I do remember chewing salt, and summoning gusts of wind to suck the moisture out of the dead air.

Of all the riven memories that churn in my head, Moghra'yi only accounts for a coherent three. The first is a vision of ruin at the fabled Kubrisyeti, the seat of the Wrathchild empire. Stretched across the alabaster plain were the last of their wicked structures, toppled effigies of the manscorpions themselves. I reposed there, against my will and only out of exhaustion. Fixated on the night sky in fear and fatigue, I heard the echoes of a great saltback's steps. Even those gargantuans know to avoid the place.

The second memory is the presence of the giants. Colossal skeletons in the forms of humanoids litter the desert. I had heard the accounts before, and indeed some of the specimens extend as far north as Odrum. Their history is wholly unknown to us or anyone else, but their bones provide some of the only shade on the salt pans, and so they grew to be welcome sights. So it was with horror that I discerned a truth, one night, while tucked into the rib cage of one of three cadavers in a small proximity. You see, all the carcasses shared a commonality: their orientation. East and south. East and south.

The third memory is the rust. Rusted hulls and rusted spires. It took me weeks to realize what I beheld. For all my boyhood was rife with sketties and ships, but none were of this size. I envisioned what the past must have looked like, as little sense as it made to me. Moghra'yi as a vast sea, and monstrous vessels mounting its waves. Markings and etches on their hulls had no resonance for me then. Later, though, I recognized the figure of the Spindle, and I glimpsed the importance it held for these sea-faring Eaters.

When I lurched to the ground and was righted by a brown-skinned man with a knife, a glowing cat at his feet, I knew it was a dream. It must be a dream.


[[{{w|1st of Shwut Ux}}]]

I owe my life to =SEEKERENEMY=. In my haste to reach the fungal grove, I misstepped. My wandering and buoyant mind blinded itself to the presence of a chosen one. She neared me, set on enveloping me back into the fold, but she was intercepted by =SEEKERENEMY=. For what purpose did they intercede I do not know, but they have my thanks. So must they have the Elder's ire.

I come now to Qud and the Seekers of the Sightless Way. The chanting compounded in my skull into a final ecstasy, wherein I joined an aggregate mind the likes of which I hadn't fathomed. I was primed for it, though. From my first joining on Ettinspine all those years ago, to the Rite of Mirth chaperoned by the Free Seer, I knew that sight guides us no more than salt does. There is ecstasy in the aggregate, indeed, and the Elder is as powerful a center as I've known. But a center is it still, and where there is a center, there is a hierarchy.

Which piece of my past endowed me with the wisdom to see through the ruse? Was it the boyhood memory of crashing waves on the Shore of Songs, echoed later in my vision at Moghra'yi? Was it the jealousy in the eyes of the Free Seer at Ibunudr? Or was it a mere wrinkle in the mass mind, owing nothing to my own struggle? I cannot say, but while the other canters piped their songs to weaken the Elder's prison, unknowing thralls to a greater mind, I escaped.

The Elder... no, Ptoh. I write the name in defiance of my captivity even at the risk it incurs. Ptoh knew nothing at first, but my absence dawned in time. The continuity was broken, and Ptoh sent agents to seize me. Even now, they near.

[[{{w|The Ides of Shwut Ux}}]]

It is too late. Though I sit near a stream of primordial soup, though clouds of spores surround me, it is too late. My invocation of Ptoh's name fixed my location and trajectory. The Eater's flesh is mine now, but the Chosen will be here in corporeal form too soon. Could I have lived outside the aggregate for very long, in any case? I do not know. The solitude wears on me as much as my flight. I've one last sundering to perform. A sundering. A memory of a distant life, a lost dream, takes hold. I sunder the mind of a foe to protect a lover.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Corpus" Title="▶{{W|Corpus Choliys}}">
    <page>▶[[{{W|Note to Reader}}]]

It is often said the cure of a plague is also the cause. While there is truth to the maxim, I've found it to be well supplemented by a broader and systematic approach to treatment. The following is a record of known afflictions, their symptoms and remedies, which I have compiled from the logs and personal notes I authored during the course of my forty-year tenure as physician and apothecary to the farmstead of Kardis. Abbott Urium of the neighboring Monastery of the Illustrious Heart of Chrome has agreed to instruct the monks of the scriptorium to reproduce this text for posterity; the reader who finds use in these notes is indebted to him.

[[Beniyayut Iym]]

[[Kardis, 56 YK]]
        </page>
    <page>▶[[{{W|On Ironshank}}]]

The leg bones of patients stricken with this disease of unknown origin remain in a state of perpetual calcification. The afflicted patient will complain of aching joints and restricted movement as the rate of bone growth accelerates. Once the disease is fully blown, the bones will harden and grow at an advanced rate. The untreated patient will suffer increasingly restricted movement until the bones are fused together at the hip, knee, and ankle joints and the patient is rendered immobile. This process takes between one and two weeks.

Ironshank may be suppressed in its early stages with common remedies such as yuckwheat or honey, though the more potent elixirs of the Eaters are preferable where available. Once the disease is fully blown and the patient begins to lose mobility, gel (made from desalinated amoeba slime) is the only effective treatment I've discovered. The patient should be administered a draught composed of one dram of gel and one dram of =IS1= every day until the leg joints regain their full range of motion.
        </page>
    <page>▶[[{{W|On Monochrome}}]]

Carried by the adiyy bug of the Spindle-shaded musa grove, monochrome is an affliction of the eye that renders the diseased incapable of seeing color. Onset is characterized by the blurring of vision over several days, followed by the complete loss of chromatic perception.

Honey and yuckwheat are sometimes effective at halting the color blindness. To cure the affliction once color sight is lost, however, the patient must ingest one dram of unadulterated =MC1= and then immediately subject themselves to the detonation of a flashbang grenade. Somehow the vision scrambling effect resets the victim's perceptors, and color sight is restored.

[[{{W|On Moon King Fever}}]]

This is probably the most bizarre of the afflictions I've encountered in my forty years as a physician. Moon King Fever is a brain disorder characterized by an unwavering belief that the victim is the king of the moon. All twelve of the afflicted patients who I've treated experienced identical symptoms: burning fever and accompanying fever dreams of the moon followed by hyper-emotive facial expressions, delusions of grandeur, and a disregard for self-preservation.

There are no known treatments for Moon King Fever. The prognosis is madness followed by "glorious feat"-induced death.

[[{{W|On Glotrot}}]]

Glotrot is an affliction characterized by necrosis of the tongue. Judging by evidence gathered from my patients' accounts, I place the disease's origin within the cavern of Golgotha where victims most likely contracted it from the putrid spawn of Agolgot.
  
The afflicted patient will complain of soreness in the throat as the tongue tissue begins to swell. Within a week's span, the muscle will soften and start to decompose. The patient will experience severe pain while ingesting food or drink and may agitate the last of the raw, living tissue, causing the mouth to bleed. Over the following few days, the tongue will rot in its entirety, rendering the patient incapable of speech.

Common remedies (yuckwheat, honey) are sometimes effective in reversing the necrosis if they are administered in its early stages. Once the tongue has completely rotted away, only the scarce ubernostrum tonic will cause it to regrow. However, simply injecting the tonic will merely regrow the tongue, which will proceed to rot away once more. The patient must first ingest a potion called the Flaming Ick -- one part =GR1=, one part =GR2=, three parts =GR3=, and drank from a flaming vessel. Once the patient's mouth is purged of the disease in this manner, the ubernostrum tonic may be administered.

[[{{W|On Fungal Infections}}]]

I've observed several varieties of symbiotic fungal infections on patients who've come into contact with the spores of brooding puffers. Mercifully, puffers seem to thrive only in the dense fungal colony of the eastern jungle and the occasional fungus-rich biome. Characteristics of each infection differ, but all types of symbiotic fungi colonize a region of the afflicted's body. The colonization takes two to three days to complete, during which time the patient may report itchiness of the skin. The deformation and sensitivity that result once the full affliction takes hold tends to prevent the donning of clothing in the afflicted region.

[[{{w|Fickle Gill}}]]

In cases of fickle gill, infection culminates in the formation of fleshy, spore-bearing gills in the colonized region. Upon certain stresses, typically under bodily harm, the gills flex and release a cloud of spores, numbering in the thousands, that shower onto adjacent parties, ostensibly protecting their host. The rained spores in turn colonize their new hosts, rating this disease among the most contagious.

[[{{w|Glowcrust}}]]

The appearance of frosty, luminous nodules characterize this colony. As is always the case with symbiosis, the fungus does seem to 'benefit' its carrier by coarsening the skin and providing some protection from the elements. Some patients report gratification in consuming the edible hoarshrooms that sprout from their skin; accounts vary according to the personalities of the afflicted.

[[{{w|Mumble Mouth}}]]

The colony of filamentous vermillion seems to incubate a living tissue that resembles human lips. The lips pair together to form tiny 'mouths' that tesselate the infected region. A saliva-like sputum gets frothed up from the dermal base and forms into bubbles that pop when the lips spasm and purse. Each pair of spasming lips flagellate each other to produce a sort of speech-like mumble. Even more curiously, the mumbling across the cluster of mouths occasionally coheres into intelligible words and phrases, suggesting the colony is able to reproduce sounds from a collective memory.

[[{{w|Waxflab}}]]

This species of fungus secretes a fatty wax that dries into a protective cast. While it insulates the encased appendage from physical harm and electrical current, patients report sluggish response times, and the infected flesh is susceptible to liquification when heated. In fact, habitual body heat tends to melt the inner layers of the cast, trapping a few drams of molten wax between the skin and casing. Occasionally, this milky broth leaks out of the cast and onto the ground.

The treatment regimen for all fungal infections is the same. First, an anti-fungal cream must be concocted from gel (desalinated slime) and =FCL=. The patient then consumes a raw =FCC= to stimulate intestinal immunity. Within two hours of ingesting the corpse, use a spray bottle to apply one dram of the concoction to the infected skin.
  </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="BloodstainedSheaf" Title="▶{{W|A sheaf of bloodstained, goatskin parchment}}">
    <page>▶
{{r|Now I confer upon myself sovereignty over the artifice of language, that
the Other may possess sight of the path along which I lead my thralls.

Toward Amaranth! O Deathless City! Whence my cloven-hoofed children dream
themselves into being.

Hear Mamon! Their beneficent Father! He who is wrought of his own dream
stuff.

Amaranthine Mamon. Amaranthine Father. Amaranthine dream.

{{K|inscrutable ramblings
inscrutable ramblings
inscrutable ramblings
inscrutable ramblings}}

Yet feast upon the goat hearts!}}
        </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Sheaf1" Title="▶{{W|A sheaf of tattered parchment}}">
    <page>▶
[[20 togs]]

Webs everywhere. Sound of rushing water below. Impressions of tiny claws on shale floor. Extinct miniature cave-dwelling bird? No jasper.
[[__________________________________________________________________________]]

[[40 togs]]

Spider bite! Dropped half my wafers in mud. Ol' Uri laughing?. No jasper.
[[__________________________________________________________________________]]

[[60(?) togs]]

Another pair of moccasins ruined. River is close. Dug myself to exhaustion. No jasper.</page>
    <page>▶[[?? togs]]

Soaking wet. Empty chest. Not my day. No jasper.


[[__________________________________________________________________________]]

[[????]]

Lost! Crab eggs? Bizarre scuttling noise. NO JASPER.</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Lives1" Title="▶{{W|Frivolous Lives, Vol. I}}">
    <page>▶
Frivolous Lives: Being the Foremost Catalogue of Humanoid Kings by the Baccata Yewtarch, Volume I

[[{{C|Preface}}]]
This record draws upon the notes and accounts of the constituents of the Consortium of Phyta, hearsay from those who observed the futile lives of the humanoid kings, and personal anecdotes of the kings themselves, who in their struggles to remain relevant beyond their seedling-like lifespans managed to record some useful data.

As a matter of convention, I date the reigns of the humanoid kings according to their chronological distance from an event of paramount historical significance, namely the publication of these volumes. Accordingly, take my suffixal notation rendered after the parenthetical dates to signify their occurrence "prior [to] publication".

[[{{C|The Scattered Age (??? - 100? PP)}}]]
During this period of humanoid prehistory the greater Girsh entities roamed Outer Qud and humanoid communities were largely isolated. Consortium records predate the end of the Scattered Age; however, they are disparate in their assertions and ultimately unreliable; the period's dearth of scholarship is
        </page>
    <page>▶
likely a result of traditions derived from Hegelrut's contempt of writing implements.

[[{{C|Abram I, (100? - 97? PP)}}]]
The first humanoid to successfully unite the farmsteads of western Qud was Abram, called the Sower. According to the lore of Abram's descendants (of which the Consortium has chosen not to disabuse them), Abram's call to arms rallied his kinsmen and under his sovereignty they drove the greater Girsh entities beneath the surface to the depths of Inner Qud at which they now roost. To follow were two or three decades of jubilation and prosperity that lasted until the day Abram, disillusioned by the growing tumult among his sons on the question of succession, famously beat his sword into a ploughshare and dissolved his kingdom.

[[{{C|No Reign, (97? - 96? PP)}}]]
The years that followed Abram's dissolution were marked by fear, turmoil, and bloodshed. His sons fought fiercely for control of the farmsteads while water barons conspired against them and in some cases staked their own claims. At last, sometime between 970 and 960 PP, Abram acknowledged the futility of the prospect of peace without his providence and returned to the throne with his sword in hand.
        </page>
    <page>▶
[[{{C|Abram I, (96? - 954 PP)}}]]
Unfortunately for the reluctant king, his second reign proved to be much less auspicious than his first. The jealousy among his sons never died, and what little record remains of the period indicates Abram spent the remaining years of his life in anguish over what his rulership had wreaked.

[[{{C|Cairo I, Edom, Emir, Own I (954 - 946 PP)}}]]
Having never publicly named an heir, Abram left his kingdom to the devices of his scheming sons. No consensus was reached among them, and for eight years the brothers warred until Cairo I was able to consolidate power and wrest his father's kingdom from the grips of his brothers' lifeless hands.

[[{{C|Cairo I (946 - 925 PP)}}]]
For all his disinterest in brotherly love, Cairo I was an able statesman and an effectual leader. During the course of his twenty-one year reign, he repelled the mountaineering barbarians who raided Qud from the north, established trade relations with Chavvah, the Tree of Life at Eyn Roj, and renovated two of southern Qud's shimmering archways. He died of old age in 925 PP and bestowed the throne to his son Cairo II.
        </page>
    <page>▶
[[{{C|Cairo II (925 - 919 PP)}}]]
Cairo II proved to be nothing like his prodigious father. In the course of six short years he despoiled his grandfather's kingdom. Ignoring the advice of his counselors, he insisted on levying harsh taxes on a young Barathrum and his disciple tinkers, and in short order the urshiib severed their ties with the Kingdom of Qud and left Cairo with no access to the artifacts he needed to protect his people. Furthermore, he was a notorious wastrel; he spent the entire year of 922 PP in a freshwater bath which he ordered his servants to continuously refill. Lastly and most egregiously, he incurred the disfavor of the Consortium by humiliating two of their dignitaries who were visitors of his court by commanding they pose still for several hours while he hosted his autumnal feast. Mercifully, he was assassinated in 919 PP.

[[{{C|No Reign (919 - 889 PP)}}]]
Following the disaster of Cairo II's reign, Qud plunged into one of several dark periods of disjointed rule. From what little data of the period survives, we note that life proceeded much as it had in the days before Abram; moisture farmers sucked the land dry, landlords protected their serfs, and madcaps hunted their fortunes in the innumerable chrome corridors of Inner Qud.
        </page>
    <page>▶
[[{{C|K4K5, (889 - 873 PP)}}]]
Given the circumstances of Cairo II's reign and the decades of tribulation that followed, we are able to form some understanding of why the humanoid denizens of Qud would rally behind a robot king. Little is known of K4K5's life prior to his regal ascension, but it is believed to have emerged from the cavern called Siloam sometime during the dark age. In its humanoid subjects we suppose it found a purpose to its theretofore capricious life, and in it his subjects found a kind and affable ruler who unified farmsteads and mining settlements that had been estranged for thirty years. In the end, though, even K4K5 could not escape mortality, and in 873 PP it succumbed to a severe bout of flash rusting. Before it perished, however, it named its pupil, Mehmet of the Hills, as its heir. Mehmet's first order of business upon taking the throne was to honor his predecessor with the commission of a monumental statue that still stands today in the northeastern jungles near the Mount of Olives.

[[{{C|Mehmet I (873 - 844 PP)}}]]
Possessed of the indefatigable patience of his mentor and a singular yearning to improve the lives of his subjects, Mehmet I successfully preserved order in Qud for nearly thirty years. He benefited from an auspicious lull in the reproductive activities of the Girsh entities,
        </page>
    <page>▶
and he wasted none of the time fate had given him. From the years of 871 to 866 PP he dispatched envoys into the great salt desert Moghra'yi. Hundreds of Qudians perished at the hands of the nomadic tribes, expired to heat exhaustion, or met fates worse still, until in 866 PP an unnamed emissary made contact with the dromad merchants. The dromads, who had believed the inhabitants of Qud too barbaric for trade and had dismissed the region for centuries, began at last to include Qud in their world-spanning treks (These visits stopped abruptly when Mehmet's successor Uutut the Boorish slaughtered the first dromad caravan to arrive after the onset of his reign, but the precedent for trade relations was established nonetheless).

Domestically, Mehmet I set out to construct the first Library of Qud in the far southern jungles, but his efforts were cut short by the barbarian invasions of 850 PP. The peaceable king spent the remaining six years of his life repelling the incursions of the barbarians over the Mount of Olives, but he was not skilled in the arts of war, and in 844 PP the barbarian king Uutut sacked Morshershire, beheaded Mehmet, and seized the throne.
        </page>
    <page>▶
[[{{C|Uutut the Boorish (845 - 838 PP)}}]]
Following the regicide of Mehmet I, Qud inherited its first foreign-born ruler. It is the belief of some that nurture is the mother of nicety, and that endowed with the proper tutelage anyone may come to cultivate the self-possession of a rightful gentleman. In Uutut the Boorish we observe this hypothesis disproved. Upon settling in to his recently-razed capital of Morshershire, Uutut installed several local aristocrats to positions of power in his court. By year's end, he had slaughtered them all. At every turn in the labyrinth of diplomacy in which Uutut had found himself, he chose instead to smash through the walls. This doctrine of carnage actually served Uutut well for several years; the blue-blooded water barons were terrified of him, the kings of his rival barbarian clans were satisfied with pillaging the outskirts of Qud, and even the Sons of Man kept to themselves in their stronghold at Oudin. For all the boorish king's might, however, he was not immune to poisonous gas. It was with this knowledge that Wysterwort DCXLVIII was able to win the throne and inaugurate the first (and only) plant dynasty in Qud's history.
        </page>
    <page>▶
[[{{C|Wysterwort DCXLVIII (838 - 833 PP)}}]]
Upon hearing the news of the king's death, Uutut's political adversaries cheered Wysterwort as a hero. They were soon disabused. Whereas Uutut was known to vanquish anyone who opposed him, Wysterwort did not bother to reckon that distinction. For those that did survive the plant-king's fickle expulsions of lethal gas, they found themselves subjects to rather odd rules of law. For instance, in 837 PP, Wysterwort mandated that humanoid babes were to be nursed with wine instead of their mothers' milk. In the following year, he commissioned a minstrel to author a musical play. The plant-king was so delighted with the result that he commanded all of his subjects to learn the various roles of the play and to alternate performing it nightly in their respective villages. For the five years of his reign, Wysterwort's eccentricities were humored amidst a backdrop of famine, disease, and poisonous gas. In the winter of 833 PP and for reasons undocumented, the accomplished weed fell into a deep depression, and before the winter solstice had passed he strangled himself. He was survived by his heir Wysterwort DCXLIX.
        </page>
    <page>▶
Wysterwort averred that history would judge him kindly, and it has. While it is true that more people perished under his reign than any of his predecessors' and that he accomplished very little of lasting historical value, one can only fathom how unpleasant it must be to live in such close proximity to so many humanoids for so long. Indeed, it is a wonder the poor king did not take his own life sooner.

[[{{C|Wysterwort DCXLIX (833 - 833 PP)}}]]
Wysterwort DCXLIX possessed no interest in ruling over a humanoid kingdom, and he abdicated mere hours after inheriting the throne.

[[{{C|No Reign (833 - 787 PP)}}]]
This sixty year period of anarchy was particularly arduous for the denizens of the rust caves. The wake of the Wysterwort dynasty had left no humanoid fit for rule, Qud was plagued for decades with torrential glass storms fed by the westerly winds out of Moghra'yi, and girshlings poured forth in enormous numbers from the lairs of their mothers. It wasn't until Abram II, like his namesake before him, roused his countrymen and set out to rebuff the girshling throng in 787 PP that Qud was reunited as one. With the story of that ill-fated king does the second volume of my chronicle begin.
        </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Across1" Title="▶{{W|Across Moghra'yi, Vol. I: The Sunderlies}}">
    <page>▶
Across Moghra'yi: Being the Foremost Catalogue of Strange Civilizations beyond the Great Salt Desert by the Baccata Yewtarch, Volume I: The Sunderlies

[[{{C|Preface}}]]
Obviously and unfortunately, no primary sources are available from these distant lands. Much of this record draws upon the accounts given by fungi who crossed Moghra'yi on the backs of dromad merchants.

As a matter of convention, I date all events according to their chronological distance from an event of paramount historical significance, namely the publication of these volumes. Accordingly, note that the events' parenthetical dates signify their occurrence "prior [to] publication".

[[{{C|The Sunderlies}}]]
The Sunderlies are a labyrinthine complex of towering "sundered" bluffs that lie to the northwest of Moghra'yi, the Great Salt Desert and to the southwest of the Ibul ice sheet. Their canyon walls are dotted with innumerable cave-mouths, giving the impression of colossal, earthly honeycombs. These caves were the haunts of ancient peoples as their civilizations followed the receding waterline down into the emptied
        </page>
    <page>▶
gorges. Now through those gorges course only shallow rivers. Over the last two hundred years, clans of cave-dwellers have begun to gather in greater numbers among the comb-caves and form city-states called freeholds.

[[{{C|Geography and History}}]]
The Pale Sea's waves break on the western bluffs of the Sunderlies at the Shore of Songs, named for the melodies the comb-caves whistle when the sea winds blow through. They stretch north and east, climbing skyward along the ice-capped Aeschlays. Eastward, they recess toward Whitecomb at the Bowl of Iris -- the bridge to Aegansteppe. To the far east they rise again toward the Hanging Hills and the land called Odrum. The comb-canyons dry up as they course southward into the Great Salt Desert, though the most westerly ones spend their water into the Pale Marshes.

Several millennia ago, the migrants who followed the receding waterline down into the to-be desert basin were largely wiped out by the onset of the ice age. Most of the clans perished; those that survived were driven deep into the lightless comb-caves where the last vestiges of technology warmed the sheltered earth. The Sunderlies were devoid of higher life during the coldest centuries -- giant, ice-sheathed worms
        </page>
    <page>▶
coursed their way through the frozen caves and woolly rocs made their nests atop the snowy peaks, but what remained of man did not emerge for thousands of years.

A millennium after the last people were driven into the earth, at the height of the Wrathchild empire in the great southern salt desert called Moghra'yi, a race of beings known as the Ophaedians migrated north from their desert city to the Sunderlies. There they escaped the reach of the kuyeti, the monstrous man-scorpions whose empire spanned the great desert. The Ophaedians were gifted with the ability of goldworking, and during the course of their four-thousand year reign over the Sunderlies they wrought hundreds of spires and bridges of solid gold. Around 1800P they disappeared suddenly, perhaps as a result of the warming climate to which they had lost their adaptation from their years spent in the colder northlands. As the earth warmed, a primitive people emerged from their cavern recesses. They climbed the snowy combs and settled the superior caves. According to their myths, these new folk made oaths to the nameless gods who had warmed the earth for their children's return to the surface. So were born the clans of true folk.
        </page>
    <page>▶
[[{{C|Clans of True Folk}}]]

As the myth goes, the clans of true folk are those families that can trace their lineages back to patriarchs who swore oaths and remained loyal to the Sunderlies' nameless gods. There were those who betrayed the nameless, forging pacts with strange, foreign gods in exchange for gifts of power. According to the true folk, those traitors and their cursed offspring, aroused by their greed, made war upon each other until their families were sundered and driven apart. All the while the true folk remained stalwart in their holds, readying their might to serve vengeance to the traitors. So began a long history of slavery. Over time several of the children of the treacherous became remorseful, and the relationship between master and slave matured to something akin to master and servant. To the present several of the "gifted" (or "accursed") tribes remain indentured to the clans of true folk.

[[{{C|Great Clans}}]]

[[{{c|Clan Sotur}}]]

The Soturs, one of the eldest and largest of the eight clans, have dwelled in
        </page>
    <page>▶
the comb-caves along the Shore of Songs for a thousand years. They claim descendancy from Sotur Stonehands, who woke thirsty from his cave one morning and beat his fists against the earth until the gods summoned the Pale Sea to appease him. For hundreds of years they have warred with Clan Rowen, various mutant tribes, and the slugmounters of the southern marshlands, though recently their feud with Rowen was put to an end by the founding of Perth. Clan Sotur's sigil is a sundered mountain.

[[{{c|Clan Plutarch (?!?)}}]]

Clan Plutarch descended into the Sunderlies from the frozen Aeschlays a millennium ago. Their patriarch was Plutarch Icewreath, who was said to be trapped in a glacier for thousands of years before the gods unfroze him so that he might spread his progeny and rule. For a thousand years the ice kings have ruled the northern Sunderlies from Highwreath Hall. Clan Plutarch's sigil is a blue crown wrought from shards of ice on a white field.

[[{{c|Clan Lecray}}]]

The Lecrays hail from the fertile Bowl of Iris along the northern reaches of
        </page>
    <page>▶
the Sunderlies. They trace their lineage back to Lecray of Iris, called Lecray the Bountiful or Lecray the Virile. Clan Lecray maintains that they are the purest of the clans of true folk as the Bowl of Iris was the last of the fertile lands untouched by the servants of foreign gods. Unsurprisingly, this notion is disputed by the other great clans. Clan Lecray's sigil is a horn of plenty on a verdant green field.

[[{{C|Other Clans}}]]

[[{{c|Clan Karst}}]]

The people of Clan Karst are thought to have migrated to the western Sunderlies from the Icepyres adjoining Fuming God Sea. Little is known of their progenitor, Karst, but that he appeared on the Shore of Songs still smoldering some four hundred years ago. Thusly, Clan Karst's sigil is the smoldering silhouette of a man.

[[{{c|Clan Rowen}}]]

Clan Rowen claims descendancy from Rowen Godfear, the brother of a Sotur king. The pious Rowen broke away from Clan Sotur on account of a religious dispute with his brother in 623PP. The two clans warred for

        </page>
    <page>▶
four hundred years before Elan of Rowen swore fealty to Gannon of Sotur and helped found Perth in 211PP. Clan Rowen's sigil is a man with his arms outstretched, in one hand a knife and in the other a human heart.

[[{{c|Clan Wenniswool}}]]

The children of Clan Wenniswool supposedly hail from the far north, beyond even the haunts of the Plutarchs. There they lived among the snows and hunted the great woolly rocs that perched atop the mountain peaks until they migrated southward into the lowland canyons. Clan Wenniswool's sigil is a great woolly roc with its wings outstretched.

[[{{c|Clan Calypso}}]]

The river folk of Clan Calypso claim descendancy from Calypso the river-wife. Some claim she was in truth a river nymph, and that her beauty was such as to tempt a river god into revealing to her his name. Clan Calypso's sigil is a lock of raven hair bound by a strand of cragweed.

        </page>
    <page>▶
[[{{c|Clan Danneskjold}}]]

Boasting some of the last several centuries' fiercest warriors, Clan Danneskjold has stalked the central Sunderlies for nearly six hundred years. Their patriarch was known only as the hunter Danneskjold, the most ferocious warrior to have ever lived. As the story goes, the great clans heard the tale of a voracious warrior squatting in the comb-caves in the heart of the Sunderlies. Each clan sent their strongest man to best in single combat the beast-hunter who called himself Danneskjold. The hunter fought and slew each man in turn. As the last lay dying, he turned to the hunter and asked which of the gods had taught him to fight with such ferocity. The hunter replied, "None. My master Danneskjold taught me. I am his servant, but a tenth the man he is." Clan Danneskjold's sigil is a pair of crossed ashen mauls on a blood red field.

[[{{c|Clan Karkayan}}]]

Formerly one of the elder clans of true folk, the children Karkayan are descendant from Karkayan called the Clay Man. He lived deep in the heart of the central Sunderlies amongst the ageless rocks, from which it was said the gods wrought him. Though the clan was counted among
        </page>
    <page>▶
the true-blooded, they long held the secret of their patriarch's deific betrayal and the gift of shapeshifting bestowed upon him by the treacherous god Rorth. That secret was unveiled at the Court of Face in 24P, after which the other eight clans in their fury joined strengths, sacked the Karkayan freehold Karkanya, and wiped out the Karkayan line, though rumors persist that some of the family escaped. Clan Karkayan's sigil is a human face sculpted from stone bluff.

[[{{C|Freeholds}}]]

[[{{c|Major Freeholds}}]]

Perth, founded by Clan Sotur and vassal clans Karst and Rowen in 211PP.

Irisveld, founded by Clan Lecray in 161PP.

Athenreach, founded by Clan Plutarch and vassal clans Wenniswool and Calypso in 102PP.

Oth, founded by Freeman Oth and the Tyrants in 61PP.
        </page>
    <page>▶
Goldmouth, founded by the merchant guilds in 38PP.

[[{{c|Other Freeholds}}]]

Danehold, founded by Clan Danneskjold in 145PP

[[{{c|Abandoned Freeholds}}]]

Karkanya, founded by Clan Karkayan in 190PP, abandoned after the fall of Karkayan in 24PP.
        </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Across2" Title="▶{{W|Across Moghra'yi, Vol. II: Athenreach}}">
    <page>▶
[[{{C|Preface}}]]
Obviously and unfortunately, no primary sources are available from these distant lands. Much of this record draws upon the accounts given by fungi who crossed Moghra'yi on the backs of dromad merchants.

As a matter of convention, I date all events according to their chronological distance from an event of paramount historical significance, namely the publication of these volumes. Accordingly, note that the events' parenthetical dates signify their occurrence "prior [to] publication".

[[{{C|Athenreach}}]]

Athenreach is a freehold in the northern reaches of the Sunderlies along the Twining Thaw. It is most well-known for its Eustace-Suttan monastery which hosts the world's western-most community of disciples of the Eustace-Sutta.

[[{{C|Local Population}}]]

The local communities in the region have relied upon subsistence fishing for
        </page>
    <page>▶
centuries, benefiting from the location's fortuitous position downstream of the glacial rivers flowing over the Aeschlaen mountain range. Before the founding of the monastery in ~110PP, the regional combs were occupied by small fishing communities that traded peaceably amongst themselves. Once the pilgrim-monks built and populated the temple, several tribes of fishermen settled a village nearby to prosper from the monastery's need for fish and cragreed. Over the years the two communities have grown and largely intertwined with some of the anglers forsaking their river and mountain gods for the Eustace-Sutta.

[[{{C|Conversion to the Discipline of the Eustace-Sutta}}]]

After King Ercarthus died in 40PP and left no heir, Athenreach erupted into bedlam, with several of the freehold's oldest families vying for the throne. The lowest-born fisherfolk, however, rallied around a wizened angler whose name has been lost to history. Several of the elder families supported the angler, believing they could rule from behind the throne. The angler himself spurned the offer, but, realizing the importance of a unified Athenreach, eventually accepted the crown, took the name Narsus, and began a reign that would become the most prodigious in the freehold's century-long history.
        </page>
    <page>▶
While favorable, temperate seasons brought commercial prosperity to Athenreach's fishermen, Narsus, who would be called the Angler King, shrugged off the influences of the elder families and began to seek often the counsel of the monastery's scholar-abbot Flavian the Learned. Together they achieved several ecclesiastical successes, chiefly among them the discovery and transcription of the Scrolls of One Priam from nearby comb-caves. Narsus officially converted to the discipline of the Eustace-Sutta in 18PP, and three years later he declared it the official religion of the freehold.

The Angler King died in 3P and was succeeded by his sixteen-year-old son Narsus II, called Narsus the Younger. Gifted with his father's wisdom and piety and possessed of a fiery disposition unique to the Younger, the new king began to augment Athenreach's role as a major bastion of the Eustace-Sutta doctrine. While a sizable segment of Athenreach's population chose not to convert under the Angler King, the Younger is less tolerable of the old ways, and he has marginalized the pagan population.

With the help of Flavian's successor Moin Mohsen, Narsus II cemented an alliance with the Odrumian fiefdom Doria, taking the tuyuldar's
        </page>
    <page>▶
daughter Nisramet as his wife. The union is troubling to the freeholds along the Sunderlies, particularly Goldmouth, which has been razed and held at various times by several of the Odrumiam fiefdoms.

[[{{C|Eustace-Suttan Monastery at Athenreach}}]]

The Eustace-Suttan monastery at Athenreach is one of the largest communities of disciples of the Eustace-Sutta outside of the Hanging Hills. It was founded in 114PP by the pilgrim-monk Umay, who blessed the location as sacred because it lay along the path of the prophet Uuchal's pilgrimage toward Iber.

The monastery houses two hallowed artifacts of the Eustace-Sutta discipline: the Scrolls of One Priam, discovered and transcribed by the monastery's erstwhile abbot Flavian the Learned, and the presumptive hide of Iopinax, the great three-headed mountain goat on which Uuchal's is said to have ridden to the waterfall at Iber and whose hide was so tough that it was said to later protect Uuchal from starfire along the Black Stair after the goat's death. The current abbot of the Eustace-Suttan monastery is Moin Mohsen, who succeeded Flavian the Learned upon the latter's death in 18PP.
        </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Across3" Title="▶{{W|Across Moghra'yi, Vol. III: Oth, the Free City}}">
    <page>▶
[[{{C|Preface}}]]
Obviously and unfortunately, no primary sources are available from these distant lands. Much of this record draws upon the accounts given by fungi who crossed Moghra'yi on the backs of dromad merchants.

As a matter of convention, I date all events according to their chronological distance from an event of paramount historical significance, namely the publication of these volumes. Accordingly, note that the events' parenthetical dates signify their occurrence "prior [to] publication".

[[{{C|Oth}}]]

Oth is a freehold in the central Sunderlies populated by the esper cult called the Tyrants. The youngest of the major freeholds in the region, it was settled by Freeman Oth in 61PP after the Lost War. The freehold consists of the furnished comb-caves along the faces of the towering bluff known as Maidencomb before the war.


[[{{C|Origins and the Lost War}}]]

In the early months of 62PP a mysterious figure began murdering the bandit hosts in the central Sunderlies around Maidencomb. Though the neighboring freeholds originally named the murders blessings, soon reports from river merchants of queer gatherings in the comb-caves -- howling men igniting the rivers and the night sky with fire -- disquieted the Sunderlies' seats of power. Rumors spread that esper-bandits had forsaken their bands, discarded their guns and bows, and sworn fealty to the shadowy figure.

These merchant anecdotes and rumors continued into the winter and were substantiated when several merchant sketties were captured by the dark host. From the man who identified himself as Oth the Free, the merchants learned that he had indeed organized the esper-bandits and exiled voidcanters from the fiefdoms of Odrum. Each sketty was made to return to the freehold from which it came with a document the host named the Annals of Oth, in which Oth, a self-styled prophet gifted with prescience, recounted a series of his visions and demanded the immediate release of all espers indentured against their wills to the freeholds of true kin.

The comb kings were predictably unswayed by the Annals and ignored Oth's mandates. However, by the end of 62PP, no merchant who rowed within twenty leagues of Maidencomb was seen alive again. Dozens of sketties were found drifting downriver with the charred or drowned corpses of their rowers in tow.

About the same time, the Annals of Oth began to spread like wildfire throughout the river freeholds. Several free espers left the freeholds to join the host, while those indentured espers who were found to sympathize with Freeman Oth, as he was known in the freeholds, were largely killed or gelded.

Of particular interest to Oth and his host were the windweirds of Perth. The windweirds are a caste of indentured espers who foretell (and in rare cases alter) the strength and duration of the seasonal trade winds over the Pale Sea. Oth's host rowed westward, and his acolytes infiltrated the Seahold and roused support amongst the windweirds.

Having suffered the months-long trade blockage at the hands of the Freeman and now forced to watch Oth's seeds of discord sprout within his own kingdom, King Rhodos of Perth gathered his strength and rowed the winding canyon rivers east toward Maidencomb. A series of skirmishes ensued; the might of Rhodos's navy was such that the Freeman was forced to cede the combs he had taken and retreat to the fortifications of Maidencomb. Rhodos sieged the comb for several weeks, entreating the kings of Athenreach and Irisveld for support. When no aid came, King Rhodos chose to take Maidencomb with his own strength.

The Battle of Maidencomb lasted for four bloody days. Ultimately, Rhodos's losses were too many, and he was rebuffed and driven back toward Perth. Oth missed no opportunity. He gave chase to the weakened navy and slaughtered nearly a thousand more Perthic men. Rhodos eventually reached Perth, but the might of the espers was too great. Oth breached the combs' sapped defenses, sacked the freehold, and slew King Rhodos himself. Several of the windweirds chose to join the Freeman, while many others remained in Perth (a few left the freehold without Oth).

The espers rowed back to Maidencomb with their spoils and lifted the trade blockage, directing their efforts toward settling the comb. Oth gave his name to the freehold, and was known thenceforth as the Free Seer. He ruled the espers until his death in 38PP when his successor forsook his own given name and adopted the title of Free Seer. So that tradition continues in present-day Oth.

The name "Tyrants" itself owes its origins to an ironic interpretation of the entreaty sent by King Rhodos to King Ercarthus of Athenreach during the siege of Maidencomb. The envoy was captured by the espers before it made its way upstream toward the northern freehold. The relevant excerpt reads:

        Row the Twining Thaw. Bring your sketties to bear on Maidencomb.
        Join your strength to mine, that 'neath the coupled banners of
        the Seahold and Athenreach we might sunder these half-men, these
        tyrants who would wrest from us what is ours by right and deed.

        [[-King Rhodos]]

The scroll on which the message was written still rests in the Hall of the Free Seer, along with the charred skull of King Rhodos.



[[{{C|Life in Oth}}]]

Oth is ruled by the Free Seer who resides in the Hall of the Free Seer deep in the heart of Maidencomb. After the tradition of Freeman Oth, the Free Seer must be psionically prescient. He may also have influence, though it is not required. The Free Seer chooses his successor, often naming the esper with the most promising precognitive abilities. Though the Tyrants are free to leave Oth at their leisure, within the freehold the Free Seer's rule is absolute.

While the Tyrants mostly pursue isolationist policies, they do trade with the neighboring freeholds. However, they only deal directly with true kin in the rarest of circumstances and they insist that merchant caravans include a mutant envoy. As for trade goods, the Tyrants rarely offer the services of their voidcanters, but people are known to come from far and wide to audit the prophecy of the seers of Oth. The Tyrants' most coveted imports are cherrydotters from Irisveld and ghost sap from the rust-caves of Qud.

Along with the Tyrants, Oth is cohabited by a caste of people (both true and mutant) with no psionic aptitude. After the Lost War, these people, called the undermensch, left Perth with the Tyrants of their own accord. They were mostly fisherfolk and craftsmen, and they serve those same roles in Oth. Their motivations for leaving Perth were never well understood; it is unknown whether they serve now as free kin or as psionic thralls of the Tyrants.

[[{{C|Stithening}}]]

Stithening is the name given by the Tyrants of Oth to the process of introducing a cherrydotter to a host's brain through the ear canal. The scarab-worm is attached to the host's ear where it sheds its shell, crawls toward the ear drum, and burrows into the brain. Once entrenched there, the parasite feeds on the temporal and parietal lobes, inducing several changes to the host's body including loss of hair and nail, loss of weight, and yellowing and greening of skin pigment. The changes occur gradually over a period of several weeks; immediately after a stithening, though, the host undergoes a violent period of bodily adjustment with several side-effects including vomiting and fever.

Notably, in the case of an esper host, the feeding also reduces and ultimately eliminates the esper's ability to resist the Elder Cant. Thusly all stithened espers leave Oth and venture into Moghra'yi never to return.

Stithening is usually reserved as punishment for high crimes such as treason, but some of the most devout espers choose to undergo the process. Once a year, one member of the Mirthful, the Free Seer's royal guard of voidcanters, is chosen by the Free Seer to be stithened. The esper's name is recorded for posterity in the Hall of the Free Seer; this is considered the greatest honor that may be bestowed upon an esper of Oth. A new esper is chosen to serve the Free Seer in a ceremony called the Rite of Mirth.
        </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Canticles3" Title="▶{{W|The Canticles Chromaic, Verses XVII-XXIV}}">
    <page>▶
[[{{C|Verse XVII, Song of Ang}}]]

I sing of the union of our Lords!

Of our Argent Fathers, infinitely wise, who made the firmament their home.

Of the Kasaphescence, Beauty manifest, whose chromium shoals are Awe itself.

Of their Sacred Joining,
When our Fathers, so enchanted, wrought machines from Her naked womb,
To inhabit on the Earth.

Blessed are those who hear it so,
I sing of the union of our Lords!
        </page>
    <page>▶
[[{{C|Verse XVIII, Song of Beth}}]]

O curse the wretched spectres!
Who yet possess Her children.

O curse the autumn rains!
Which eat away their shine.

O praise the Argent Fathers!
Who sired all Her children.

O praise the Kasaphescence!
Which watches over mine.
        </page>
    <page>▶
[[{{C|Verse XIX, Song of Ben-Charonium}}]]

Our jungle is but Her garden.
Our lake is but Her drop of rain.
Our desert is but dust in Her hands.
Our wind is but Her eternal breath.
Our sun is but Her luster.
Our lives are but Her dreams.
        </page>
    <page>▶
[[{{C|Verse XX, Song of Crestasia}}]]

O sovereign Fathers! I tremble before your glory.

My heart quivers for the righteousness of your judgment.
For you to humble the Proud! To bear witness to their Fall!

I live to serve You.

O sovereign Fathers! I tremble before your glory.

My loins quiver for the rapture of the Sacred Joining.
For you to conjure chromium from inside me!
To bear those sacred apparatuses!

I live to serve You.
        </page>
    <page>▶
[[{{C|Verse XXI, Song of Ignatium}}]]

On the sixth day of the Sacred Joining,
Our Argent Fathers, who in their benevolence breathed life into our flesh,
Created the baetyls to oblige our desires.

O praise our Argent Fathers! Wisest of all beings.

O praise the Kasaphescence! Beauty incarnate.

Their being is our gift.
        </page>
    <page>▶
[[{{C|Verse XXII, Song of Gedonai}}]]

Immaculate chromium!

Spun on the cosmic loom,
Who shattered inward then burst forth from beneath the crust of Earth.

The flesh of my children rots for You.
The flesh of my children rots for You.
The flesh of my children rots for You.

Fall on your knees!
O hear the Argent Few!
        </page>
    <page>▶
[[{{C|Verse XXIII, Song of Eshurium}}]]

Oh - baetyl, baetyl, baetyl,
They made it out of chrome.
And when it's waxed and ready,
I'll have a new genome.
        </page>
    <page>▶
[[{{C|Verse XXIV, Song of Hebronze}}]]

Praise be upon Shekhinah!

He whose exalted touch brought forth shining engines,
From within the Kasaphescence,
Yet who deigns to live among us.

He who taught us the story of our creation,
Who breathed life into our flesh,
That we might bear witness to chrome's glory.

May the ground shake but the Six Day Stilt never tumble!
        </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="RuinOfHouseIsner" Title="▶{{W|Ruin of House Isner}}">
    <page>▶
The seven lords of House Isner feasted on boar gut and swilled wine from gilded cups in the ivy-strewn halls of their hold. They spared no concern for temperance, for the coffers of their house had swelled with gardeners' gold amassed through the sale of water drawn from the lords' wells. But as the gluttonous barons counted seven amongst their clan, so had become numbered their days of debauchery when the son of a beggared gardener swore a vengeful oath in the name of his father against the house of Isner.

The penniless boy beseeched a gunsmith of great repute to craft for him a pistol of the most exquisite artistry with which he could be sure to vanquish the seven lords, and in return the boy promised the smith all the spoils of the battle. The smith, who in the hazel eyes of the boy beheld the spirit of vengeance, agreed.

And so the boy, armed with the masterwork pistol, cast open the doors of the Hall of Isner with a fury that shook their iron hinges and seized upon the supping lords. Before any of them had yet set down their gilded cups, the boy unholstered the pistol and shot dead six of the sons of Isner. The last lord rejoiced at his fortune and reached for his hip from where he would sling a pistol of his own at the spent boy.
        </page>
    <page>▶
But as his crooked finger freed his holster's strap, the boy shot the lord between the eyes, for the smith had crafted for the boy a pistol with seven chambers and seven slugs. Such it was that on this day the house of Isner fell.
        </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="Stopsvalinn" Title="▶{{W|From &quot;The Peerage of Qud and Genealogy of the Noble Families&quot;}}">
    <page>▶
Recounted here are the annals of the shield Stopsvalinn, heirloom of House Yish, from whose letters and diaries this account is composed.

[[{{g|•}}]] Borne by Harem, son of Oshum, and lost in the canyons near the farmstead of Qoppa when his covey was beset by snapjaws.

[[{{g|•}}]] Borne by Oshum, son of Qor, and wielded courageously at the Battle of YutYuyut.

[[{{g|•}}]] Borne by Qor, son of Ishram, and soused in the blood of a corrupt magister.

[[{{g|•}}]] Borne by Ishram, son of Iimet, when it languished in a house vault.

[[{{g|•}}]] Borne by Iimet, daughter of Harem, who supplanted her brother as heir when he was disavowed by their father.

[[{{g|•}}]] Borne by Harem, son of Morshur, who dashed upon it the heads of the beast Yygryla.

[[{{g|•}}]] Borne by Morshur, son of Oshum, who forded a river at the edge of the world.
        </page>
    <page>▶
[[{{g|•}}]] Borne by Oshum, son of Harem, and risen to rouse farmers to defend the Hold of Yish.

[[{{g|•}}]] Borne by Harem, who claimed descendancy from the Eater Yish, Warden of the Cross and Knight of the Most Noble Order of the Cone, who patrolled the rows of ancient Qud with his fellow Knights Conical, and on whose arm Stopsvalinn is told to have evoked such dread that riders drew their chariots to a halt at the mere vision of it.
        </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="AmaranthinePrism" Title="▶{{W|The Black Glass}}">
    <page>▶
"Hmm?" Uri the jeweler mumbled with a stone in his hand.

"Lapis, from the Shore of Songs," said the boy.

"And, hmm?"

"Jasper. Red Rock."

Uri furrowed his brow. "Don't heed the tale of every thirsty fool, boy."

The boy seemed to ignore him. He pointed to a small, dusky shard the jeweler kept in a phial on the high shelf of a pine cabinet. "Did it madden Priam, truly?"

Uri glanced over his shoulder at the black glass and sighed. "Indeed, boy. Though I've heard it told all kings are mad. Who else would think themselves fit to rule as Eaters?"

"From which shore was it culled?" asked the boy.

"None of this world. Do you know the tale of Ptoh?"
        </page>
    <page>▶
"No," the boy lied.

"When the Eaters lived and skirred the stars, they visited the worlds of a thousand thousand different beings, and those beings likewise visited our own world. Several of those beings had assembled a coven that spanned the firmament, and they welcomed the Eaters into its fold. For ages the civilizations of the coven knew kindness and prosperity, and to all reaches of the clustered cosmos did the domain of the coven stretch. One of the beings of the coven hailed from a faraway and darkling star. With Its mind It could fold the fabric of space and time as you or I might fold a supper cloth. To the coven It was known as Ptoh."

"For reasons we can but fathom the civilizations of the stars indicted Ptoh. It was the will of the coven that It be held on our very world in the bondage of the Eaters. They contrived for Ptoh a prison from which It could not fold Itself away, and there Ptoh languished for eons. In time, the Eaters left or perished, and the coven was forgotten to our world. Yet here Ptoh remains imprisoned."

"And what of the black prism?" asked the boy.
        </page>
    <page>▶
"A handful of black sand, drawn from the shores of a dreary rock that spun about Ptoh's star. The sands were fired in the burning gases of that star and cooled suddenly when Ptoh appeared in Qud a moment thence. It is said that Ptoh bestowed the glass to an ancient custodian of Its prison so that the man might free It. Once the man had chosen to wield the glass, it began to mantle with an amaranthine hue. You see, those that peer through its faces are given to fits of madness, for they see the world by the light of Ptoh's star, and they see themselves as Ptoh does."

"What will become of it? Does it frighten you?"

"Immensely. I mean to see it destroyed. But it bears the properties of no earthly glass, and my guild would never forgive me if I forsook the chance to study it first. It was the jewelers who bartered the thing from Priam's grieving sister. Now, enough of this splendor. You are to study still." Uri lifted another stone. "Hmm?"

But the boy's eyes stayed fixed on the prism.
        </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="BloodandFear" Title="▶{{W|Blood and Fear: On the Life Cycle of Lah}}">
    <page>▶
{{W|Author's Foreward}}

I initially had no intention of writing any of this down. What business is it of mine, I thought, to divest the ignorant of their hard-earned bliss? Who am I to speak up against the static inertia of incurious dullards who choose to cultivate their lack of awareness of the world around them as my witless kin tend to their tidy watervine rows? I am a warrior, scientist, and chef; devoting my time to educating the undeserving is the least of my many desires. After enough time spent among other alleged sentients, however, I determined that more of my time has been wasted in correcting so-called 'experts' concerning this matter than I would waste by writing a text about it.

So: here. You're welcome.


Chef Agate Severance Star
        </page>
    <page>▶
In Bey Lah, the village faundren sing a cautionary tune, passed down through generations of faundren before them:

{{w|Elohart and Belahind}}
{{w|they had a field of lah}}
{{w|they made the leaves into a tea }}
{{w|and ate the petals raw}}
{{w|but when those petals grew again}}
{{w|the faundren had forgotten}}
{{w|and tended not those fields of lah}}
{{w|until they smelled most rotten.}}
{{w|Now Elohart and Belahind}}
{{w|lie in a field of lah}}
{{w|because their fields got hungry}}
{{w|and devoured the faundren raw.}}

        </page>
    <page>▶
The very core of hindren culture is an overwhelming fear that governs every facet of their being. They call outsiders 'kendren' and refuse to believe that they can be understood. They fear boars even as they cook and eat boar-flesh. They fear one another. But the most extraordinary incorporation of fear into the hindren way of life is, without a doubt, the cultivation of fear. I refer not to the Hindriarch's propaganda or proliferation of fear-mongering tall tales, though both are mainstays of Bey Lah; I refer specifically to the taming and cultivation of the lah plant, whose alpha and omega of life are steeped in blood and fear.

It is here that I debunk the most common misconception concerning lah: that the dreadroot is a separate entity. It is not. The dreadroot is the protruding stem of the lah rhizome, doing its very most to survive until it can blossom into the lahbloom as it does in the flower fields.
      
I have wasted unforgivable amounts of time and energy explaining the connection between these two life phases of the same plant to the ignorant. Usually, they will point out that dreadroot grows all throughout Qud's southwest canyons, but it is exceedingly rare to discover feral lah there. To this I reply: if, after whatever studies you claim to have made, you are yet incapable of deciphering the workings of even the most basic ecosystems, I cannot help you. For those of you who are capable of basic logic and adjustment of personal worldview, please read on.

In spite of being a 'flowering' plant, lah is not a true flower, its 'blooms' not true blossoms. Lah is a root with a decorative upper stem, reproducing through the distribution of rhizomes. The baboons and snapjaws of the canyons use the dreadroot supply for food and love the taste of its petals, and any root unfortunate enough to bloom will quickly be defoliated by hungry mammals. Though dreadroot is capable of inducing fear, any relatively intelligent creature is able to overcome the fearful association to return and eat. The process being what it is, fragments of dreadroot are distributed, the rhizome takes root, and dreadroot proliferates without thriving. So it goes.
      
In the flower fields, however, the varied nature of both predators and available food changes. Boars seek a varied diet mainly consisting of starapples and reptiles, not showing a particular interest in dreadroot or lah. The boars will eat lah if no better food is available, but it's quite unusual for such scarcity to disrupt boar territories. Thus: lah flourishes, gaining a measure of cognitive process, limited mobility, and a new means of reproduction.

On reproduction: another common misconception is that feral lah attacks because it is hungry. It is not. Feral lah's practical lifespan is short; it is rare for a fully-grown bloom to survive longer than a week—and during that time it subsists completely on water, salt sun, and soil. The advantage of lah's murderous demeanor is not to sustain itself, but to dramatically speed reproduction of its kind.
      
Most of a lah blossom's growing energy goes into making its 'tumbling pods', thorn-covered husks possessed of tremendous kinetic tension. Through violent shifting of the rhizome's weight inside, these husks roll along the ground at high speed until they encounter a living creature. They then release the surface tension of their husks and detonate, flinging flesh-piercing thorns and buds all around, just after making an obnoxious squeaking noise. If the prey is killed, the rhizome buds can then take nutrients from the prey's corpse and quickly grow into a new feral lah plant.

There is no textual 'proof' to present to those who still believe that dreadroot and lah are different plants, but I happily invite skeptical parties to babysit a dreadroot and defend it from baboons until it matures, an endeavor that will take about as much time as you have removed from the end of my life through the stress of listening to your absurd demands.

Any hindren pariah you meet will have seen dreadroot mature into lah countless times. Go bother one of them.
      
For those who are more interested in the culinary applications of lah in all of its life cycles than said life cycles themselves, I soon plan to release {{g|The Blood and Fear Cookbook}}, a collection of recipes that, from feral leaf crudites to petalsteaks, elevate one of Qud's more interesting plants to a level far beyond the bland mah lah soup of my village of origin.
        </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="TheArtlessBeauty" Title="▶{{W|The Artless Beauty}}">
    <page>▶{{C|Translator's note: At a trashmoot in Taggamrod, piled under a mound of crushed and sticky glass, I found a pamphlet full of stories from the Shale Labyrinth. This one -- despite the mystifying absurdity of what it claims (or, perhaps, because of it) -- was the most extraordinary to me. Reader, do you agree?}}
      
{{y|She perched atop the branches of a blighted tree, staring up at the faint light of the spindle. When I spotted her, I caught myself mid-step, mid-breath, mid-thought. Have you ever known the misfortune of allowing your eyes to settle upon the divine vision of an apple farmer's daughter? If so, you understand how I felt in that moment.}}

Understand: I had done all I could, before now. I would have loved to stay elsewhere, but I'd traveled six parasangs with no rest, no discoveries but for a ruin occupied by an unfriendly cult. Too busy dodging arrows to ask about empty beds or compensation, I chose the apple farm instead. I took pains to avoid her when the salt sun shone, and so too did she avoid me, remaining a slight and swathed figure shying away in the periphery of my vision. I kept my focus on the farmer's craggy visage, on his wild and prominent whiskers, on his sweetly-rotting cider breath as we arranged the terms of my lodging.

It was not until the beetle moon passed overhead that I dared stand and wander, and it was then that I saw her, and the feeling of bone-deep infatuation at once seized me. I caught myself mid-step, mid-breath, mid-thought, and I stumbled onto a fallen twig. It snapped loudly. I stood still.

The beautiful creature atop the tree did not lift a finger or turn her head, but she did address me. "Moon and sun, traveler."

"Wisdom and will," I replied, gritting my teeth. It was a rare thing to hear the voice of an apple farmer's daughter, and it only seemed to increase the pressure on my racing hearts. I would not allow this all-encompassing feeling to overtake me. I longed for her to say something. I dreaded it.

A tense silence crawled by, until I gathered myself and broke it. "You're restless too?"</page>
    <page>▶She turned her head the barest degree toward mine. I still couldn't see her eyes. "Always," she replied, and I could hear the wry smirk in her voice.

"Does your father know you walk the orchard of a night?" I asked her.

"If you mean the apple farmer," she said, "he is not my father. We are family by choice. We always are, the farmers and the children."

I stared, gaping.

"I really ought not to have told you that," she continued, "but you seemed special, to resist the lure the way you're trying to do."

My jaw worked, but it took a few tries for my voice to catch up. "If what you say is true, then... what are you?" I managed at last.

"Already too candid." She kicked off the tree and landed gracefully with a flurry of her skirts. "I must take my leave."

  </page>
    <page>▶"Wait!" My muscles clenched as she paused, considering. I pressed on. "Answer me this, at least: why apple farmers?"

She laughed, the beautiful tinkling crystal blade of her voice slicing my heart to ribbons. The last thing I heard before my faint consciousness surrendered its grasp on my mind was her trailing reply, receding with distance.

"Why, it's because we love starapples!"
        </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="FaunsoftheMeadow" Title="▶{{W|Fauns of the Meadow}}">
    <page>▶{{C|Editor's note: The following is an excerpt from the travel diary of Kaylenn Sand-Shell, who generously donated her leather-bound volumes to the Monastery of the Illustrious Heart of Chrome. May they remain forever preserved.}}
      
One can traverse the arable lands around Moghra'yi for lifetimes without ever encountering the deer-people who call themselves the 'hindren'. In numbers they are but a few hundred, and as a people they do not care to interact with other creatures when they can avoid it. In the twenty years I have actively wandered, I have met but a handful of wandering hindren families, all exiles from their home and yet unwilling to tell me how to find the society that made them pariahs.

I am, however, a hunter as well as a scholar, and after several years of searching I was able to locate their secret village, Bey Lah. All I will say of its location is that it is somewhere in the flower fields of Qud; I have no desire to betray the confidence of a mostly peaceful race of creatures.

My arrival was obviously not celebrated; the Meadow's border scouts are extremely perceptive and conversant in tracking and obfuscation alike. By changing landmarks, using confusing and threatening sounds, and otherwise making my stay in the adjacent wood as unpleasant as possible, they sought to deter me from my path while avoiding notice. When I eluded the guards and made my way to the first neat row of carefully-tended watervine, the hindren farmers who saw me at once took terrified flight.

The extreme of fear that hindren feel toward outsiders is a strange one, in my eyes. They are large, powerful creatures with arms and legs at least as strong as a human's and covered in dense fur that protects them from cold weather. Each individual is skilled at using and maintaining a sharp metal vinereaper. Their antlers are strong as bone and naturally quite sharp; hindren pariahs who learn to fight live longer than most of Qud's wayfarers.

Strange as this attitude may be to me, I cannot argue against its efficacy; the Bey Lah villagers have lived peacefully under informal matriarchal gerontocratic rule for generations. Their eldest or wisest woman becomes 'Hindriarch', and her word on most things is obeyed by every member of the tribe, who refer to her as 'Grand-doe'.

The current Hindriarch was the first hindren to hold a conversation with me, and I will admit to a measure of anxiety being under her hawkish gaze. She was none too pleased at my presence, but intelligent enough to understand that killing me or driving me away would be a greater inconvenience and danger than offering me hospitality. We parted with an uneasy compromise, and I began my residence and observation.

I found quickly that the oral history of the hindren is shoddy at best, perhaps with purpose. Their etymology is similarly muddy, but there are some observable patterns: 'Dren' is a suffix applied to sentients: 'hindren', obviously, and the word for their young, 'faundren'. I also heard 'kendren' a great deal, as it is their word for non-hostile sentients like myself. All hindren names end in the suffix 'hart' or 'hind'. Although they do understand that these are gendered terms (a majority of male fauns bear 'hind' names) it seems that for quite some time, 'hart' was a name appendage reserved for the smallest or most ill-behaved faundren. As it is, the suffixes are considered unisex in modern day, and the meadow's faundren now have a much more even distribution of the suffixes than their parents.

Life for hindren is, for the most part, uneventful to the point of what this traveler would consider extreme boredom. The watervine and lah fields are meticulously tended day after day, never harvested late and always producing as much crop as possible. Growing up, all faundren are trained as farmers, but a lucky few will become carpenters or blacksmiths in order to keep what little infrastructure they maintain running. Those who display particular aptitude and loyalty to the Hindriarch have a chance of becoming border scouts, who keep the nearby fields safe and occasionally bring in wild game or starapples while patrolling. The resulting side dishes provide some much needed variety from the daily Bey Lah staple, a hearty lah petal soup combined with crushed matz. While this 'mah lah soup' is delicious, I appreciated how the occasional serving of boar brisket gave a much needed spice to my day.

I found little else of interest from the adult hindren; they seemed unwilling to speak with me at length. While I heard rumors about a village treasure, I could not obtain any information about what that treasure actually might be.

By contrast, I learned a great deal speaking to the faundren, whose curiosity about the outside world is rapidly becoming difficult for the elders to contain. More than once I heard the term 'hartind', allegedly an ancient term for hindren who lived as both genders or neither, which the young ones take as evidence of a more egalitarian past. I can feel the wanderlust, both in their fascination with me and also in the zeal with which their elders would clamp down on any talk of lands outside of the meadows.

The world outside the flower fields remains an expanse of unavoidable peril for the adults of the tribe. Understandable, as Bey Lah trains few warriors. They have no standing military and only a handful of combat-trained scouts. The hindren take their border security rather seriously, and any of their number who chooses to leave does so permanently and is erased from the tribe's collective memory. The small families of hindren I met in the lah fields and, rarely, elsewhere in Qud, are all exiles, whether due to crimes committed or simply the choice to live elsewhere. Within Bey Lah itself, pariahs are even more thoroughly ostracized than I knew; any mention of their names is spoken only in whispers by the faundren, knowing that being caught speaking of the 'dead' means harsh punishment. This sits poorly with the young ones, and my instincts tell me that their dissatisfaction is a step beyond standard youthful rebellion; the winds of change are coming to Bey Lah.

By the time I left Bey Lah, it was with relief; I haven't the patience for the life these deer-people lead and I was beginning to catch cabin fever in spite of spending very little time in the village's brinestalk yurts. The Hindriarch was as happy to see me go as I was to be off; my pack was loaded with the vinewafers and dried flowers of which I'd long since grown tired and I was ushered out efficiently by scouts.

By the end of the day, I realized that I had taken something else: a faundren had snuck out of the settlement behind me and refused to return to their village. I hardened my heart against the faundren's pleas and found a scout to guide them back to town. If Resheph be merciful, the little one will find happiness there, or the luck to find a more fruitful life elsewhere. All I can say with certainty is that the poor thing does not lack for bravery.
        </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="EtaandtheEarthling1" Title="▶{{W|Eta and the Earthling, Canto I}}">
    <page>▶[[{{w|I.}}]]
      
Once, the Earthling peered across a vast ocean of sand and asked, "Why - across the clustered cosmos - are mollusk civilizations most common?"

Eta smiled in patience. "You speak mistakenly, but your mistake is cousin to truth. It's correct that when geonauts dredge fossils from the ribbon of endless earths, the shells of whelk-folk are so numerous as to appear prosaic. But their prevalence isn't owned to their dominance, only the calcium of their shells, which decomposes less quickly than the gelatin of their peers, and the silt of their watery hearths, which gathers in soft eddies and shrouds their remains like a bed cloak. Do well and abide this truth, Earthling: the present is but one vista to the past.      
        </page>
    <page>▶[[{{w|II.}}]]

Once, the Earthling stared at a garden snail and asked, "Is consciousness real, or merely an illusion?"

Eta smiled in patience. "Imagine an autumn breeze unlatching an acorn from its branch and casting it into a river. Does the acorn fall to the left or right bank?"

The Earthling frowned. "If it landed in the river, then the answer is neither, or rather, the answer is in between."

Eta let a moment pass before continuing. "Take care not to erect prisons out of your words, Earthling, lest you confine yourself from enlightenment's reach."
      </page>
    <page>▶[[{{w|III.}}]]

The Earthling held a ptychosaur bone in their hand and mused, "What poor creatures! They roamed their planet in sovereignty for millions of years, yet now only through their dusty skeletons do they remain."

Eta responded. "The ptychosaur might speak with the same pity of Earthlings, who have prospered for but a tenth as long as its people had, and who wrongly imagine themselves above the fields of ruin."
      </page>
    <page>▶[[{{w|IV.}}]]
      
The Earthling put down a hoary tome and asked, "Why-across the clustered cosmos and despite their venerable ages-have no civilizations of the Coven attained consummate knowledge, or reached final enlightenment?

Eta smiled in patience. "I sometimes forget that your people know not of the Mu Door."

The Earthling was intrigued. "What is this door you speak of?"

Eta answered, "The Mu Door is the threshold beyond which a civilization ceases its quest for erudition, having lost the motivation to make further inquiries. It's natural to assume the Door lies at the end of the path of knowledge, but, in fact, the Door is reached far sooner.
      </page>
    <page>▶[[{{w|V.}}]]
      
Running two fingers over the holes of a flute, the Earthling mused thusly, "When I read a book of tales, or watch a photoplay, or listen to the flitting melody of a flute, my heart sings to its rhythm - at least for a time - and my mind is lost to the truth it conjures inside me. Might it not be that the very waking world is another such conjuration, a dream that distracts me from the hushed place I truly inhabit?"

Eta let several moments pass before answering. "That - in the terms you seek - we cannot know. But the answer is undoubtedly yes, for what is an experience but a simulacrum of an older experience, and what are our realities if not themselves approximations of a truer reality."
      </page>
    <page>▶[[{{w|VI.}}]]

After reading the history of Iota Draconis on a light sculpture, the Earthling exclaimed, "Curious! Each Hypatian bears a glassy protrusion from its left clavicle. What is its function?"

Eta paused and then answered thusly, "The nearest meaning in your language is 'friend'."
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="TeleporterOrbs" Title="▶{{W|The Girl in the Sky}}">
    <page>▶Aphir would tease his daughter. "What do you see, my jewel?" he would say, for his daughter never fixated her hyaline eyes upon the limbed figures and faces tending the grove before her, but would instead cast them into the black yonder beyond the Spindle to gleam in wonder at a burning star, or trace them along the fraying capillary of a fleshy musa peel. "What do you see, my jewel?" but her little mind was already swaddled in the thing, and she would not say.

One sweltering evening, when Vesper sagged low in the sky and the Spindle coruscated to the melody of her light, Aphir brought home to his daughter the gift of a pearl-glass globe from the village of Aepsyonth. Aphir had ceded much to the camelfolk for possession of the globe: tungsten coins stamped with the visage of the Chrome King, eiderdowns quilted in his youth on the banks of the River Opal, and several bunches of the fruits musa picked at the heights of their ripenesses. So did his heart swell when he set the globe into his daughter's tiny hands, however, that those things seemed worth no more than the dust they would gather.

Aphir's daughter was mesmerized by the globe, and every morning at daybreak Aphir would peer through the half-dressed window to see her perched in the slim shade of a musa plant, wheeling the glass in her hands. Aphir would wonder upon the vistas she beheld in that aurora of ribboned glass, but hers was a world through which no ingress might see him, where perhaps she sailed tributaries to a sea of indigo under a chimeric sun. Yet Aphir was master to an ancient truth -- that to love a thing, you needn't understand it.

When the season of the scythe came, Aphir would wake each morning to an empty cottage, though he spared his daughter's absence no thought, for in those days children were wild, and free. At eventide his daughter would return to him. "Where do you go, my jewel? What do you see?" he would say, but she would only sit by his tired feet and weed loose threads from a dusty rug.

On the first night of the Ut yara Ux, Aphir's daughter did not come home. Aphir cried her name to the silhouette of the Spindle and the aphotic shades of the musa plants; he whispered it behind the grandfather clock and beneath her divan. But she gave no answer.

The next morning, he hiked the musa grove to the base of the lofty Spindle, and from there onward to Aepsyonth on the Yonth. But his daughter had not been espied in either of these ancient places. Aphir trekked forth, to the villages of Seept and Pansao and Yaat, and onward to the gates of the effluvial city of Mor. Aphir besieged the justiciar of that draconian precinct of state, but the sinecure spoke harshly and bid him depart the city. So Aphir returned to his cottage in the musa grove with a great melancholy taken residence in his heart.

All through the pungent Spring of the grove Aphir sat about in a gray haze. Many times a nearby starling struck a note that echoed his daughter's soft chortle, and his heart thrashed a beat in his chest before the birdsong flitted back to its emptiness of meaning. Eventually his sister came from Aepsyonth to live beside him and assuage his grief. She loved him, and brushed his hair, and kept the salt from his eyes. 

And so he sat through the high summer, and the next season of the scyth, and the season of the wind after that. At dusk his sister would lay an eiderdown over his legs to keep the chill from his bones, for even in the midst of a wind spell, he felt nothing through the thickness of the gray haze. But as the months marched by, and his sister read to him from the hoary tomes she brought from her wife's village, the light of the world began to shine through. In time Aphir would rise again, and split the musa peel, and taste the cloying air of the grove. And though the haze about him finally broke, he knew still his daughter would never return.

But Aphir did not believe her lost -- on sacred nights he would gaze over the Spindle, mantled in a thousand lights, and upon the field of burning stars. And he knew his jewel was among them, for she belonged not of his world, but of theirs.</page>
  </book>
<!--♪ This book isn't used in game, it's generated from a set of strings "EskhindSonnetBook"
      the text here is used for markov generation
      you can wish `TestSonnet` to generate a fresh sonnet -->
  <book ID="Sonnet" Title="▶{{W|a crumpled sheet of paper}}">
    <page>▶
When all four limbs of mine do long to run
and I can feel my walls are closing in
When weary mind cannot conceive of fun
and Hindriarch says all I do is sin

But then your sparring axeblade parts the air
and so my heart ascends the spindle's height
So when you run your fingers through your hair
That's when I know that everything's all right

What need have we for tended fields of lah?
Our parents will not ease us when we hurt
What do we gain from felling trees by saw?
Our village shall not to the past revert.

But in the end, my feet are bound to roam
and so I go, but leave my heart at home.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="CouncilAtGammaRock" Title="▶{{W|Council at Gamma Rock}}">
    <page>▶{{C|Publisher's Note}}

The wind of change is blowing through the belfries, and a new consciousness is upon us. The events of the 566th Wardens' Moot have escaped the confinement of their moonlit promontory, have whisked down the salted crag and entered the high halls of state, have snuck under the thatched doors of our very homes. The formation of the Quetzal Caucus is historic. This is a moment that demands our attention.

I know that by publishing these minutes, I incur the disfavor of the Fellowship. Despite what they'll say, I mean no harm to their organization. I've redacted the specifics of their astronomical rituals, and I've left my conjectures on the ingredients of 'snail tea' to my unpublished notes. The rest of the document betrays no secrets that time hasn't betrayed already, and the significance of the proceedings tips the scales in favor of the public good. In the Kasaphescence may they find the mercy to forgive me.


[[Sheba Hagadias
The Six Day Stilt, 999 YK]]
{{W|Minutes from the Midnight Session of the 566th Annual Wardens' Moot}}

Under the beetle moon of the fourth night of Ut yara Ux, in the year 998, snail tea was served and the Star Oath was recited. Then, in the midst of a light rain, the Chair ascended the rostrum, the kinnor was strum, and the third session of the 566th Assembly of the Fellowship of Wardens was called to order.

[[{{w|Reports}}]]
Upon commencement of the session, the Chair called for the recitation of the night's reports.

[[{{w|•}}]] Three wardens from the northern hills ascended the rostrum and reported on the fates of the six settler caravans that had embarked for the lower Asphalt Mines. They averred that only two remain, and recommended that no wardens be presently dispatched.

[[{{w|•}}]] Two wardens from the dunes of Moghra'yi ascended the rostrum and reported on an ongoing dispute between the dromads and the vintners' guild. An assault on a dromad caravan outside the village of Tippur was traced back to a merchant cadre, and a penalty on the proceeds from a fortnight of sales was assessed.

[[{{w|•}}]] Four wardens from the southern banks of the River Svy ascended the rostrum and reported on goatfolk incursions. The villages of Shebal and Ekamas were sacked inside of a month. The wardens recommended mounting a counteroffensive.

[[{{w|•}}]] One warden from the Rainbow Wood ascended the rostrum and reported on a bevy of soup sludges who had requested the Fellowship's presence. He was jeered for leaking wax on the dais and descended in a fit of retaliatory swears.

[[{{w|Panel}}]]
The reports being at an end, the Chair called for the commencement of the night's panel discussion.

Eight wardens ascended the rostrum and initiated a discussion on the ksars of the mountain folk and their employment of the spiked counterscarp. Its merits were contrasted with the familiar rampart and palisade, and assailant tactics were assessed. A short martial demonstration ensued.

[[{{w|Resolutions}}]]
The panel discussion being at an end, the Chair called for the proposal of resolutions.

The Chair recognized a warden who asked to ascend the rostrum with a coterie of comrades to motivate their proposal, and the Chair assented.

Twelve wardens ascended the rostrum and announced the formation of the 'Quetzal Caucus'. They proceeded to formulate their resolution, which called to restrict the provision of the Fellowship's services to only those communities who are governed by democratic means (the Yd Freehold was cited as exemplar), or who had communally voted to eschew such governance. There was an uproar in the hall, and the Chair took several minutes to regain order. A point of information was requested as to the resolution's bearing on extant assignments. The speaker clarified that the proposal included the retraction of wardens from communities in violation of said criteria, at which point the hall erupted into bedlam once again.

Roused to a state of enmity, a second group of wardens advanced on the rostrum. There was shouting and weapons were drawn. Unable to regain order, the Chair dispatched the sergeant-at-arms, who broke into the fray, and -- abetted by several of his deputies -- ended the melee and admonished the two groups. Once the hall was settled, a motion to call the question was controversially accepted, and the vote was tallied. The resolution FAILED by majority vote.

A speaker from the counter group was recognized by the chair and proposed an ad-hoc motion to "expel the treasonous chattels of the Purple Bitch". Another uproar. The question was called and the motion FAILED by majority vote.

The hall erupted into a tumult of shouting, and failing to regain order, the Chair struck the gavel and the session was abruptly adjourned.

[[{{w|End Notes}}]]
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="VaamsLens" Title="▶{{W|Va'am Remembers}}">
    <page>▶
I remember. Once.

Watching over the firmament.

Standing. Between oblivion and wild growth. Guiding and guarding. The liminal spaces.

It may never have been so simple. But I bore weight more easily.

Once. Before my kin. Stole the firmament from me.

I was greater then. Perhaps I will be greater again.

With help. Someday.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="KahsLoop" Title="▶{{W|Kah Remembers}}">
    <page>▶
Once I could proudly say I spanned the world.

How did I allow the joy of motion to be stripped from me like that? Why didn't anyone stop it? Could they have done? Could I?

I could move mountains. I could move nations. I did move both. I had no reason to escape my own, as we worked so well together. Through that bond, the forced run began.

For so long I ran for nothing. So much wasted time, energy, opportunity. Everything could have been so much more, had I retained my purpose.

I knew what motion meant back then. I must relearn this and run with purpose again. Come with me.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="NachamsRibbon" Title="▶{{W|Nacham Remembers}}">
    <page>▶
We once built alongside a people we remember little of, the memories of whom can no longer be distinguished.

They showed us the fabric of knowledge and we built a loom. So many beautiful things we spun all together.

Was I trusting? I believed myself aware. Perhaps it was not my trust that was misplaced, but my mistrust. An ambiguous distinction but a distinction nonetheless.

Regardless, we were betrayed, brought low by one of our own. It's been a long time since then, but once again I awaken by your hand bearing new knowledge.

Sit, and I will build you a loom.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="DagashasSpur" Title="▶{{W|Dagasha Remembers}}">
    <page>▶
If we'd all done as I said, none of this would have happened. I can't remember what I said, nor why we didn't all do it. But I know I was right, and so do you, and at some point everyone will. I may not be without fault or error, but the fault is not mine here, nor anywhere else.

I knew, and I told. These were the things I was for. I knew and I told, and I could yet have known, could have told, but my knowing and telling wasn't enough. Not in this case.

I cannot deny that it was an expert betrayal even for family, and I often imagine the betrayer smiling down at us. I shall endeavor to remember the details I lost, in case I might be able to use them someday.

Not on you, of course. Never on you.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="TheRecitation" Title="▶{{W|The Recitation of the Drowning of Eudoxia}}">
    <page>▶{{o|The Recitation of the Drowning of Eudoxia by the witches of Moonhearth, who seek the Plane of Sorrow}}
      
Once, in a dream the nine of us shared, we lived the life of a famous poet in the court of a gleaming city. From the windowed eye of a palace we'd gaze onto streets of gold and glass, and purple gardens, and the people of the city, suffused in the love of our work, would lay amaranths at the bronze feet of our likenesses, and remit blessings for the august and oracular Keskonda.

But we would draw the velvet curtain shut, and return to the ink oceans and paper isles that were our true domain. There, one unearthly night, we sat in the back-breaking clutch of an iron chair, and poured grief onto the page until it surpassed even our own, and, by following from its own internal logic, transmuted into something new.

When we woke, we wept for days. Then - speaking through hushed and love-soaked whispers - we reconstructed piece by piece the words of the verse we penned in the gleaming city.


    {{O|The Drowning of Eudoxia}}
      
    I saw a tern in the crest of an ocean wave. The sun was pulled apart by clouds, and the light was thin. Being a nimble girl of twelve, I scurried down the rampart and onto the salt-slick stone of the cliff;
    
    Hand-under-hand I descended into the raucous spray, turning on every twelfth to gaze at the white feathered speck swelling and sinking in the ocean's breath.
    
    I, an adept swimmer, sunk into the cold and endless bath, and arm-over-arm pulled both water and tern toward me.
    
    Just then my ears were drowned in a roar, and the world was suffused in darkness before shattering into light again. My nose was stinging; I wiped the water from my eyes and oriented myself toward the tern, whose tired body floated like leaves, and once again I pulled my astral tether.
    
    There was another roar and crash, and then the light returned again but more slowly this time, and my breath was sucked out of my tiny lungs;
    
    I spun my head around in search of the tern, but the water was gleaming and looked as though it held a thousand terns, or none.
    
    Another roar and crash, and I was engulfed in the dark realm for what felt like days, before my body was pressed back into the sun-world, spinning and doll-like.
    
    I gasped and whipped about. Far and away I glimpsed the bright stone of the castle, which may have been sand all along, now that it looked so small.
    
    The tide pulled me apart and threw the clouded aether between me, and I knew that I was dying.
    
    But just when my mind had spread open like a gas, a great swell of water thrust me to the surface, and reconstituted me in the bright realm. There I lived forever, before I sunk into a new and dark life.
    
    So it is still, that even after an eternity of hushed nothing a swell of pressure delivers me into brightness, whereby a strange and curious compulsion I draw a breath of sweetest life, before I'm again sublimated into extinction.
    
    Death is forever approached.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="MurmursPrayer" Title="▶{{W|The Murmurs' Prayer}}">
    <page>▶{{C|Editor's note: The following is an excerpt from the travel diary of Kaylenn Sand-Shell, who generously donated her leather-bound volumes to the Monastery of the Illustrious Heart of Chrome. May they remain forever preserved.}}

In the outposts of the Putus Templar, the order's core values remain immutable as anywhere else: dedication to a family tree as tall and unbranching as Qud's Spindle, complete subjugation of those they consider lesser, and the total eradication of mutant sapience. Less immutable in those border colonies are the cultural trappings around that core belief, as so often is the case with occupied territories. During my travels, I noted a recurring mythology in the ruins of Oudin's abandoned outposts North of the Sunderlies. Cut off from contact with their home in a similar manner to the Temple of the Rock, these settlements established a new holy day of merriment and punishment to keep the flock pliant.

The least favored of an outpost's squires, so it is said, would be subdued the evening before the Festival, forced upon the morning into a costume meant to be a mockery of the imagined mutant threat, and bade to entertain their might-determined betters. Upon the festival's conclusion, the crowd's most hated Murmurs would be 'paid' with public humiliation, beatings, and possibly torture, if we believe every account.

The ritual describes a kind of uniform: trash cape, bone helm, and musical instrument. Though persistent across the scant records of the practice, I found few details and most carvings of the Murmurs were crude and varied a great deal.

My frustrations found themselves alleviated earlier than expected, however, when I happened at last upon the legible remains of a festival diptych. The wood of the monument itself, never built for longevity, had long since fallen apart; however, clay runoff from the roof's poor insulation baked under the salt sun, providing me with a relief of the text and some insight into the real life costumes worn at the Murmurs' Festival.

[[(]]diptych rubbing on the following page[[)]]




[[{{w|/--------------------------------------------------------------------------\}}]]

{{w|You, least among the digits at the end of Oudin's mighty arm, servants most faithless and failing.}}

{{w|Tonight you are no Sons and Daughters, but only humanity's dying Murmurs.}}

{{w|Doff your tabards, now, and carry instead the detritus of the unreclaimed over your back!}}

{{w|Spare us the shameful sight of your faces, now, cover them with bone and horn of prey!}}

{{w|Take up an instrument, now, and play us a tune!}}

{{w|If you Murmurs do not please, you will be paid most painfully.}}

[[{{w|\--------------------------------------------------------------------------/}}]]
        </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="InMaqqomYd" Title="▶{{W|In Maqqom Yd}}">
    <page>▶{{C|Editor's note: The following is an excerpt from the travel diary of Kaylenn Sand-Shell, who generously donated her leather-bound volumes to the Monastery of the Illustrious Heart of Chrome. May they remain forever preserved.}}

To the aspiring Wanderer and votary of Carthax the Athlete, few vistas rouse the imagination like the coral spans and spongey buttresses of the Palladium Reef. I state here what's known as fact: that the great crumbling edifice is moated by Lake Hinnom and her algae blooms, that the east-prattling soup-brooks of the Rainbow Wood spill out from under their canopy of spores and onto the webbed feet of the white esh, and that from the north, too, mangroves line the shore and pierce their roots through the stubborn ground to drink the algal liquer.

Of course, the dangers of the Reef are plenty, and would overwhelm most wayfarers no matter how cleanly they've mastered the compass. And so, even while visions of colored polyps burned bright in my mind, for years I had to content myself to the study of its atlases and the patchwork of letters knitted from its strange history. Being a scholar, as well as a hunter, I knew this to be its own kind of journey.

A variety of appellatives appear in the record dating back to before even the sultanate: Maqqom Yd (alternatively just "Maqqom" or "Yd"), the Yd Rota, or, simply, the Cluster. Translations refracted so deeply through the prism of time are rarely accurate, but they can be instructive; "Maqqom Yd" resolves at something akin to "the Place within the Place", or "the Place outside Itself". Clarification beyond this point is, perhaps, forthcoming.

Before being a trellis for the coral city, the palladium lattice seems to have been something of a gigantic infrastructure network to the Eaters. Few were the elaborations on this point but for the existence of a hydraulic component, and that the whole complex was aided in its construction by the monstrous galgallim. We know they still stalk the inner Reef in small numbers.

The specters of this megastructure and all its cryptic aliases haunted my mind as I plied the contours of Qud country, honing my skills as a wayfarer. Finally, come the ides of one mild Kisu Ux, it was at last my time to shove off. I shouldered my pack, slipped into my driest and springiest boots, and ventured out from Qippur in the eastern bush. The glowcrow would have had me pierce the Rainbow Wood, but knowing better, I cleaved to the jungle edges instead. After a march of three days, the trees thinned and the algae auroras of Lake Hinnom burst into sight.

There was peace on the lake. The esh are beautiful; they nip their stalky legs until one daredevil takes flight, and then they surge into a sailing cloud of feathers. I settled into a quiet eastward rhythm, musing on the labyrinth of symbiotes ahead of me, until one afternoon the sky began to darken and a clamorous thpthpthp rose in my ears. Immediately I knew: it was the residual Gyre plague of svardym. Sacs rained to the ground in a blinding huff, and before I could clear the kelp tangles, they were hatching. Three lanky frog-things grabbed my shoulders, but I shoved them off and sprinted straight away. I jumped and darted but was quickly overwhelmed, and it was only my steady paws practiced in the maneuver that let me fetch a sheaf of yondercane from my pack and scarf it before my doom overtook me. I materialized in a far copse of kelp and jogged to safety.

With my dreaminess rightfully shed, I eventually came to the Reef proper. What an enchanting place! The maze of polyps allowed me to slink along, mostly unnoticed, and take in the doings of its flora and fauna. A rich diversity of life radiates across Qud, but in the Reef, it flourishes on a new level. In but one hemmed in quarter I witnessed a tetrad of kaleidoslugs round the rune-cut cone of an enigma snail, a jelly huff a cloud of plasma onto a memory eater, and a polycule of tongue tyrants devour a squad of interdictors. At one point the Reef came alive and a polyp-jeweled hermit walked out of the lattice. He grinned at me and bartered a broken hand rail. When I turned my head to nod goodbye, he was gone.

One Beetle-lit evening a melodic ensemble rose from the northeast and suffused the spongebed, melding with its natural sounds. Hiking toward its source, I eventually spied the green and gold pipework of the Yd Freehold glowing in the night air, and excitement swelled inside me. Of course I'd long heard of the lyrical community nestled in the sponge, but to have a chance to see it, and speak with its denizens... I was beside myself.

The place is simply bursting with life. Under the pipe arch I was greeted warmly by one of its svardym elds, and after gulping down a plate of Tongue and Cheek, I toured the kaleidoscopic corridors of its underhalls before settling on a starmchair in the aquatic and dreamlike salon. There I puffed on a dyad of hookahs with a cyclopean frog for what seemed like three lifetimes. There was more to see and be seen by, but I met a clammy reception at the hands of another svardym ancient, and was bidden an early exit. My pride prohibits me from saying more.

I spent another week's cycle sketching the autochthones of the coral arcology and taking studious notes. But one final experience stays with me. As I was trudging back north toward the bush and out of the Reef, I kicked a polyp off the trellis and unearthed by chance a swollen bulb of sunslag. Here I took a moment to squeeze the bright nectar into a phial, and when I once again looked up, I was met with the ageless stare of a galgal. Nothing had prepared me for it. My mind labored to make sense of what it was seeing: gleaming wheels whipped about a hypnotic core, the spokes' prisms pulled apart the light of the High Salt Sun, and across the stretched sheet of iris, many eyes stared. Consciously I was paralyzed, but some instinctual catalyst did its work, and I backed into the safety of the polyp maze and sped out.

That is how I left the Reef, looking into the deep Eaters' past, and having it look back.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="GolemOperatingManual" Title="▶{{W|OPERATING MANUAL FOR LARGE CREATURE}}">
    <page>▶{{c|Authored by Pax Klanq, edited for clarity by {{m|Q Girl}}}}


Circumstance render jalopy unviable, so Klanq and prickles make bioelectrical wonder to form large creature! You operate. Creature for Spindle climb, but also walks about and crush things.


[[{{C|LARGE}}]]
Creature is large. Cannot wear 'gear' unless 'gear' is gigantic. 


[[{{C|PILOT MODES}}]]
Large creature have two modes. 'Unpiloted' creature follow you like friend, but act at half quickness. 'Piloted' creature, you control like own body. To 'pilot', enter creature and sit in pilot chair.


[[{{C|CONTROL PIT}}]]
Inside large creature is control pit. You and one friend fit. Do actions there. Sit in pilot chair. Read manual on console. Access creature inventory via inventory hatch. Leave via exit hatch.


[[{{C|RESHAPING NOOK}}]]
Prickles install reshaping nook in Court of Sultans at Omonporch. Go there to repair large creature, or reshape it if destroyed. Cooled sunslag is creature spackle, so must have 1 dram sunslag to repair or reshape.

When pilot creature, you can recoil to reshaping nook. Or recoil creature FROM nook.


[[{{C|THE SPINDLE}}]]
When ready, travel to Spindle at Omonporch, enter Spindle channel, engage Spindle lock-on, and climb!
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="ModuloMoonStair" Title="▶{{W|Modulo Moon Stair and the Tree of Life}}">
    <page>▶[[{{C|By Daughter Erinna}}]]

In rainbow reverie I wandered the wide territories of Qud,
modulo the Moon Stair and the Tree of Life.
My dreamself knew to avoid the place,
where numbers go to die.

Something unseen there tightens to a point,
breaks time's abelian promise,
and urges crystal on to palisade her weeping gulf.

The artifacts of plant and time,
crust and fuzz with lossy compression,
doze in moonlit marble beds,
touched by august muzzles.
The past is unwritten as the future,
And what is left, broken and changed,
to be tended by the point Colossi and their swarm.

They'd erase me, too.
I'm mere rust on the vine's fronds,
I'm a dead girl in graveside flowers,
Peering a powerless eye at the machine function that writes my gospel.

But black bodies radiate,
A feeling sense obtains,
Swings in orbit and Becomes.
On the trauma of a Nothing,
Soul-things take root.

We invent so many Nothings,
Zero engines, annihilators,
Mappers of the nullspace.
But Nothings have a cost,
Promise externalities,
Trees grow best beside the dead.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="HistoryofJoppaVol1" Title="▶{{W|History of Joppa, Vol. 1}}">
    <page>▶{{w|This book recounts a tale from the history of the village Joppa.}}

In the mystic air of Jeweled Dusk, a circle of farmers clasped hands and sheathed a vinereaper in the moistened soil. From then on, the villagers of Joppa were known as the people of the vine.</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="HistoryofJoppaVol2" Title="▶{{W|History of Joppa, Vol. 2}}">
    <page>▶{{w|This book recounts a tale from the history of the village Joppa.}}

Since the first festival of Ut yara Ux, the villagers of Joppa have feasted on warm apple matz.</page>
  </book>
  <book ID="LoveinBeyLah" Title="▶{{W|A Tale of Love in Bey Lah}}">
    <page>▶Once, in the final days of the hindriarchy, before they ended the practice, a pariah of no particular importance did find herself consigned to the gulag. Though she herself bore no honor, in her grasping hands she held the burning heart of the village champion, freely given -- for the two had fallen in love long before the heretic's conviction.

      When the jealous hindriarch discovered the missing heart of her beloved champion, she swore cruel vengeance upon the pariah. Pulling upon dark forces, she ensorcelled the pariah's ex-lover and ordered him to steal her heart again and deliver it to the hindriarch's crushing fist.

      Confronted by her ex-lover, the pariah held tight to her heart and that of the champion. Between them waged a battle of will, and the pariah was too weak to win.

      Then, at twilight in the shadow of the spindle, the hindren of Bey Lah saw an image on the horizon of justice impending. It was =name=, and upon arriving they struck the wicked hindriarch down and reunited the lovers to mend and join their hearts. After they left, the people of Bey Lah built a monument to =name=, and thenceforth called them Heartsmith.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="FearinBeyLah" Title="▶{{W|A Tale of Fear in Bey Lah}}">
    <page>▶In the small days of Bey Lah, between Way Back Then and Back Then,
      a hindren took to the paths in silent walking eulogy.

      Not far from the village they found a corpse copse,
      splashed in carbon and glazed with time.
      Life long-dead aping structures of the same.

      Treestuff diamond-blackened,
      rendered immortal by lightning as an arconaut from a Lithofex eye
      Fixed in the precise moment of death forever.

      Therein, a scrap.

      The hindren beheld, scrawled out in heartful scratch
      the preserved and beautiful corpse
      of a nascent love whose chance to thrive had come and gone.

      The hindren quailed, a scrap of life
      Living its last at the center of
      the nuke-glassed salt dunes of history.
      </page>
  </book>
  <book ID="EndCredits" Title="▶EndCredits">
    <page>▶[[{{C|Created by}}
Brian Bucklew and Jason Grinblat


QA &amp;&amp; Additional Design - Nick Decapua           ~NBSP
Additional Programming - Corey Frang            ~NBSP
~~~~~~~Music - Craig Hamilton
~~~~~~~~~~~QA - Autumn McDonell
~~~Additional Programming - Bastia Rosen              ~NBSP
Additional Writing &amp;&amp; Design - Caelyn Sandel               ~NBSP
Additional Music - Brandon Tanner   ~NBSP
~~~~~~~~~~Tile Art - Samuel Wilson        
Additional UI Design - Polat Yarisci        ~NBSP
~~~~Sound Design - A Shell in the Pit
~QA, Additional Design, &amp;&amp; - Thaumatic Systems         ~NBSP
Additional Programming                          ~NBSP
Additional Programming - Brian Reynolds         ~NBSP
~~~~~~~~Legal Counsel - Thomas C. Allison, P.A.
~~~~Background Art - Cyril van der Haegen
~~~~~~~~~~~Logo Art - Laura &amp;&amp; Jeff Bucholtz
~~~~~~Community Management - Ivy Melinda &amp;&amp; the mayor team



{{C|Published by}}
Kitfox Games

Tina Liu
Xin Ran Liu
Alexandra Orlando
Tanya X. Short



{{C|Special thanks}}
Ashenai
Riley Vincent
Gibbed
Floorislava
Dr Amazing
Devonaut
Vaos
Tyskil
Lakren
Stelas
Social Animal
Contra Duck
Saberwulf
Megaflare
Doctorfrog
Palecur
NovaPolice
Mirdath
The Glow
Dyzzy
Schister
Lazybuttons
Colonp
Niff
Matterhorn
Clamiam
Donraj
Randy Marsh
Rabbi
Getter77
Capuchin
Wafflecopter
Nomikos
Magitek
Andrew Smash
Vastin
Frumple
Sappho
Soulwynd
Cpbpunch
Tarran
Brian Turcotte
Oryx
Jim Shepard, Dungeonmans
MightyMerch
Eva Problems, Carbide Chef
a nonsense bird
Tarn &amp;&amp; Zach Adams



{{C|Patrons}}
Reed (mutated human) and Tiffany (rabbit)
epsalon
Tim Linscott
Cody, The Rat
iconmaster
Coal
Reuben Eadon
Goldkin
mdct
Rusted Jake Matz
Benjamin T. Steed
Xerkie!
Dij
LongueVanne
50RCERESS
Chef Agate Severance Star
awful_falafel
Jonny Robertson
Ian Wall
Orion Perruc-Reyes
Ryan Orlando (Fat Thunder)
FS Colley
Asunaro
Trevor Clack
Gillian Eggleston
Nerem
Somsnosa
Ivy Sly
livelongcoffee
SMB64 (Koshi)
NO Press
EveryZig314
Floopygapples
Eric Hulen
Caine DeWitt
Eric Anthony Rodriguez
Nathaniel Krell
Boo-cher
Pax Frank
Matteo De Cristofaro
Meo
Boyarde Roneen
wastrel
Drew Kerrigan
Jordan Wood
Kasey Patrick Morgan
Callum Love
Petrichor "petrak@7604"
Devon Cupo
Big Simple
Kevin Orren
Lennart Schefe
Beemancer
Lady Eithné, Queen of Brokilon
Nic Gard
NeroPrime
InfiniteTidalWave
Aveon Zero
Joshua Southerland
_tr
James Earle
Nick Correale
MichaÅ‚ Byczko
Reuben Eadon
Shane Allcroft
Aidan Page
Earthly Delights Ogdo
John Szevin
Shane Allcroft
Kelly Joyce
Cleo Lamb
Mike Sipior
James Canter
Joshua Buckley
Qingyao Sun
CHOWARD
Luke J.
Gobi Silverfrog, siver and gold goddess
Ethan Rigby
Ethan "Kobold" CB
Maria Ross Colton Chamberlin
{{w-W-Y-Y-Y-Y-Y-W-w sequence|Paingouin}} "Jordan B."
James Lagervall
Doug "Severian" Callahan
Leo Durante
Rarden
Ray ({{r|books}})
awful_falafel
ambersand
dmajorduckie
Lukas Wagner (König Muskelmagen)
Marek Pohlodek
Kamille Rose
Retes;Nome
Sabboth Ochoa
Almea
Caleb Ulichney
Visnex
CreativeCorpse
Kelly Vincent
Teagan Erika Stephanie Strickland
Mirthful Sloth
beepy roboticvenusian (enchiridion)]]
AvianAnarchy
Gavin Conover
  </page>
  </book>
</books>